<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Quaker quasht and his quarrel quelled: in an answer to a railing pamphlet written by Martin Mason of Lincoln. Intituled The boasting Baptist dismounted and the beast disarmed and sorely wounded without any carnal weapon. Whereutno is added eighteen several meditations usually received by the Quakers at their first enterance into that delusion. By Jonathan Johnson, a servant of Jesus Christ.</title>
            <author>Johnson, Jonathan, of Suffolk?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J784</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E995_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207803</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866832</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866832</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119118</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74963)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119118)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 148:E995[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Quaker quasht and his quarrel quelled: in an answer to a railing pamphlet written by Martin Mason of Lincoln. Intituled The boasting Baptist dismounted and the beast disarmed and sorely wounded without any carnal weapon. Whereutno is added eighteen several meditations usually received by the Quakers at their first enterance into that delusion. By Jonathan Johnson, a servant of Jesus Christ.</title>
                  <author>Johnson, Jonathan, of Suffolk?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Francis Smith in Flying-Horse-Court in Fleet Street, near Chancery Lane End,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 29 August 28".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mason, Martin, fl. 1650-1676. --  Boasting Baptist dismounted and the beast disarmed and sorely wounded without any carnal weapon.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119118:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Quaker Quaſht AND HIS QUARREL QUELLED: IN An ANSWER to a Railing Pamphlet written by MARTIN MASON of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>INTITULED THE Boaſting Baptiſt DISMOUNTED AND The BEAST DISARMED and Sorely WOUNDED Without any <hi>CARNAL WEAPON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto is added Eighteen ſeveral MEDITATIONS uſually Received by the <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AKERS</hi> at their firſt Enterance into that Deluſion.</p>
            <p>By JONATHAN JOHNSON, a Servant of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <q>
               <p>To the Law and to the Teſtimony, if they ſpeak not according to this word it is becauſe there is no light in them,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 8.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>But there were falſe Prophets alſo among the people even as there ſhall be falſe Teachers among you, which privily ſhall bring in damnable hereſies, even denying the Lord that hath bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift damnation,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. Pet. 2.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>There be ſome that trouble you &amp; intend to pervert the Goſpel of Chriſt, but though that we, or an angel from heaven, preach unto you otherwiſe then that which we have preached unto you, let him be accurſed,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 1.7, 8.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Smith</hi> in <hi>Flying-Horſe-Court</hi> in <hi>Fleet Street,</hi> near <hi>Chancery Lane</hi> End, 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119118:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119118:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S Books are cenſured according to the judgement of the Reader ſo I expect no other from thee, whomſoever thou art; it is my ſatisfaction within my ſelf, that I have no other end in ſending this forth into the world, but to maintain that which I know to be truth againſt thoſe who groſſly and abſurdly do oppoſe it, as I hope will be plainly ſeen, and manifeſted to right Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Martin Maſon,</hi> the man whoſe railings ſlanders and unpara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leld evil ſpeakings againſt me, are ſounded abroad in the Nation, and for no other cauſe that I know of, for my love to the truth of Chriſt Jeſus his Goſpel: and for deſiring to draw him from that thick cloud of darkneſs under which I ſee him lie, by the deceiveableneſs of unrighteouſneſs, ſuggeſted into him by that power, that darkens the Son and the Air, and which a long time have ſtriven to hide that light and Spirit of truth, which is received by the hearing of faith preached, and believing according to the Scriptures; and now as much as ever (ſo farr as their power ſerves) in this generation called Quakers: who bouldy and audatiouſly deny Chriſt and his Apoſtles teaching, to be the Word of God, or Rule of righteouſneſs, or power of God to Salvation, contrary to the plain teſtimony of the Scripture, and calling the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures teachings, dead letter, and lifeleſs book, with innumerable ſuchlike, wicked reproachful tearms, as in the Pamphlet that I am now to deal with is manifeſted, and in many others, and as they are in their writings, ſo they are in their words, as I can witneſs and have others to witneſs with me, the one of their generation to my face told me I was a filthie creature, a lyer and a beaſt, with more ſuch foul words, for ſaying Chriſt had a body &amp; was like unto us in althings ſave only ſin, for ſaid he, Chriſt had not a body of ſubſtance but the form only of a body.</p>
            <p>And when I alledged the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> complaint of his infirmity in the fleſh, againſt their pretended perfection: he uſing the ſame lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of Beaſt and Lyar and like tould me, <hi>Paul</hi> was no Chriſtian when he wrote that.</p>
            <p>But I ſay, as for <hi>Martin Maſon:</hi> I did expect to hear of his ackno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119118:3"/>in his evil in what he had written agaiſt me for declaring the truth, which would have ſtayed me from ſending this into the world, which I have had allmoſt two years by me, but failing of my expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I ſent to him now, at leaſt to know if he were come to a ſight of his follie and evil therein, and if he were; that he would acknowledge it, if not, I muſt ſend into the world to vindicate the truth againſt him, for ſaid I, many blind ones boaſt of thy folly and my ſilence, and many who clearly ſee thy ignorance and evil therein, wonder why I will let ſuch ſtuff paſs unrebuked; but no retnrn had I from him but perſiſting in the ſame mind uſing his old language, without any acknowledgment at all. I therefore thought my ſelf further engaged, to ſend this forth which I had written.</p>
            <p>The Scriptures do abundantly foretel of the coming of theſe who in the name of Chriſt ſhall deceive many.</p>
            <p>As there is no Name given under heaven whereby men ſhal be ſaved but by the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12.</p>
            <p>So the Enemy of the Salvation knows, there is no Name but that only to take up to deceive by, and under pretence of that to bring in his low devices which are deſtructive to the Soul: there is no other way then to be ſure of ſafety in theſe dangers, when truth and falſhood hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken both one name, but to look only to the Sriptures, where the Name of Chriſt is fully made known with power, and by which whomſoever comes to right knowledge ſhall deſerue all falſe cryars of <hi>lot here</hi> and <hi>loe there,</hi> and truly know the Name and voyce of Chriſt from ſtrangers, who take up that name to deceive by, and will not ſtand to the true try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of the Scripture, but by falſe gloſſes and evil interpretations pervert the plain and manifeſt truth, and when all that will not ſerve, bouldly deny the life and authority of Scripture, and labour to pull them from mens hearts and minds, that their own falſhood may be ſet above them, as is plainly ſeen in this generation called Quakers; like to their predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors the Papiſts, all which are alike denyers of Chriſt as he hath revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led himſelf in the Scriptures: Therefore whomſoever thou art that truly deſireſt to bear the Name of Chriſtian weigh what thou readeſt in the right balance, and whatſoever thou findeſt to hold weight with the Truth, approve and receive it; and if any thing fall ſhorte of that, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it to my weakneſs, for my deſires are unfainedly to own the Truth although it be found againſt me. To the true tryal I comit my writing, who am a lover of all thoſe who love the Lord Jeſus in ſincerity.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ionathan Iohnſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:119118:3"/>
            <head>Truth Triumphing.</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OT yet diſmounted <hi>Martin</hi> from that Station,</l>
            <l>That dwelling place of Gods beloved Nation:</l>
            <l>Nor ſorely wounded, with the windy puſh</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Martin Maſon,</hi> with his quaking Ruſh.</l>
            <l>It is no Satyrs, Apiſh, <hi>Babel</hi>-frown,</l>
            <l>Can pull the leaſt of Gods beloved down.</l>
            <l>How canſt thou think thy Scrith-Owl nightly skriking,</l>
            <l>Can from Gods Truth take any Saints good-liking?</l>
            <l>Can thoſe who in old <hi>Babels</hi> ruine dwell,</l>
            <l>Reach up to <hi>Sion,</hi> or her Towers tell?</l>
            <l>Can Owls and Bats, that flutter here below,</l>
            <l>Mount up like Eagles <hi>Sions</hi> ſtrength to know?</l>
            <l>Or there diſmount from of the Fort ſo ſtrong,</l>
            <l>The Lambs Beloved, ſinging <hi>Sions</hi> Song?</l>
            <l>The more thou ſtriveſt thoſe ſacred walls to ſcale,</l>
            <l>Greater thy loſſe, the more thy ſtrength will fail.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Martin</hi> keep thou below, reach not too high,</l>
            <l>Till thou be cleans'd from thy impurity.</l>
            <l>Thy falſe conceited Wiſdom, void of Light,</l>
            <l>Lays op'e thy folly, unto wiſe mens Sight.</l>
            <l>Thy boaſting brags to <hi>Wound</hi> and to <hi>Diſmount</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Doth ſhew thy ſhallowneſſe; all men account</l>
            <l>(But night ey'd bats) thy railing Pamphlet fooliſh</l>
            <l>And thy hot zeal, to true Religion cooliſh:</l>
            <l>Vain are thy thoughts thinking to ſtrike Truth down</l>
            <l>With railing words, it never yet was known,</l>
            <l>That Truth was overcome by railing foes,</l>
            <l>Tho' many times ſhe in her Covers goes</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:119118:4"/>
            <l>With bloudy face, and Martered ſore by ſuch</l>
            <l>As ather beautious hold appears, think much:</l>
            <l>Leave thou theſe bould aſſaults' gainſt Truths rich Palis</l>
            <l>Think not that Truth can be ore' come by Malis.</l>
            <l>The more thou ſtriveſt, the more thou'lt have the foyle,</l>
            <l>And ſorrow'l be thy wages for thy toyle.</l>
            <l>Shut not thy windows at the glorious light</l>
            <l>Which in the Goſpels day doth ſhine ſo bright.</l>
            <l>Were it not madneſſe in the brighteſt day</l>
            <l>To light a candle, to ſhew men their way?</l>
            <l>What uſe for candles, where the Sun doth ſhine?</l>
            <l>As little uſe for that dull light of thine.</l>
            <l>Thy light within more ſit for ſecret place</l>
            <l>Then where the ſacred Sonlight ſhews his face.</l>
            <l>It muſt in Dungeons be, and caves below,</l>
            <l>Where Heavens bright Lamp, his face doth never ſhow,</l>
            <l>There where the nightly dancing Satyrs dwell</l>
            <l>Who likes no light but what's within their Cell:</l>
            <l>Pleaſ'd with the light themſelves there kindled have,</l>
            <l>And will no Son light let into their grave.</l>
            <l>Happy for thee if thou couldſt thruſt away</l>
            <l>That darkning skreen which hides thee from the ray</l>
            <l>Of Goſpel Son light, which would let thee ſee</l>
            <l>Thoſe glorious things which from thee hidden be.</l>
            <l>Leave thou thoſe fooliſh fancies of ſelf-teaching,</l>
            <l>And ope' thy ear to Scriptures ſacred preaching.</l>
            <l>Obey thoſe truths that therein written be,</l>
            <l>'Twill make thee of Gods holy City free,</l>
            <l>And bring thee to a right regenerate mind</l>
            <l>And let thee know that now th'art deaf and blind,</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. J.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119118:4"/>
            <head>THE QUAKER QUASH AND HIS QUARREL QUELLED, IN An Anſwer to a Railing Pamphlet, written by <hi>MARTIN MASON</hi> of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Martin,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HOU canſt not leave thy old way of boaſting, as in thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Paper, ſo in this thou crieſt up thy ſelf a man of valour &amp; ſtrength, it ſeems thou feareſt thy own Works or Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours will not praiſe thee, therefore thou contrary to Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms advice, <hi>Pro.</hi> 27.2. wilt praiſe thy ſelf, I told thee in my former Paper, That wiſe men will not boaſt till the putting off their Armour, but thou, notwithſtanding, wilt cry Victory before Conqueſt, or touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy Adverſaries with any blow, to give the cauſe of encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: thou (Bragadotio like) ſaieſt thou wilt not give one intch of ground or turn thy back on the uncircumciſed Philiſtine, by which thou wouldeſt have the world to think thy <hi>Davids</hi> heart and engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will conclude in Victory. But if <hi>David</hi> had taken thy way of railing and boyſterous braging the room of combate, or without blow he had never overcome: May not I fitly compare thee to a whore ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in her whordome, yet rails on thoſe who take her, and cryes whore firſt: I took thee in thy Boaſting, as is witneſſed in our former papers, thou runeſt out into the world and cryes me for the boaſter. But I am ſo far from Boaſting that knowing my own infirmities and weakneſs, I would rather keep ſilence &amp; let thee ſpend thy breath in vain, the wage words to maintain any ſuch right, but I knowing that thy railing is againſt the Truth, which thou ſereſt thy ſelf to oppoſe; I am mooved through mindfulneſs of the Lord not to keep ſilence. But to declare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy deeds of darkneſs &amp; preſumptious words againſt the moſt High &amp; his Saints, let this my engagement be compared with <hi>David,</hi> and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119118:5"/>thypreſumptions words with <hi>Goliah,</hi> and it will make known who is the uncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The more thou ſtriveſt the more thy weakneſs within is manifeſted, and thy ſtrokes throws thee backward.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaiſt, the weapons of your warfare, are not carnal, yet all thy defence, or offence, is by carnal foul and filthy words, of which, but diſpoſeſſe thee, and thou wilt be left without either words or ſhields. And though thou talk of the conquering Sword of the Spirit, ſaying, it is thy weapon, it is little manifeſted in thy denial of the word of God, for the conquering Sword of the Spirit is the Word of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.17.</p>
            <p>Therefore, although thou ſteal theſe words of weapons, not being carnal and Sword of the Spirit, that which thou calleſt, the dead Letter, yet art thou far from the exerciſe of ſpiritual weapons, or knowledge of them, for if thou wert not, thou wouleſt teſtifie more purity and peace. If thou ſay, thou hadeſt theſe words, the <hi>Sword of the Spirit,</hi> or, <hi>Spiritual weapons,</hi> from the light within thee, without the Scriptures, (which thou calleſt dead Letters) all that hears thee Impartialy, will ſay, thou ſpeakeſt not Truly. And ſo will thy own conſcience if thou open that Book. And will alſo let thee ſee how aſuredly evil it is for thee to call the Scriptures dead Letter, and yet fetch thoſe words which thou delivereſt for ſpiritual Declarations from thence. Thou ſaieſt (among other things) thou askeſt me, hath every one that comes into the world heard and read the preaching of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, as they are tranſcribed in the Bible, and thou ſaieſt. I anſwer, they have all heard, thou replyeſt muſt the Lyer in thee be received for the Oracle of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou hear dealeſt falſely with my anſwer, not delivering as I did, I ſaid, have they not all heard, thy error in this is becauſe thou knoweſt not the Scriptures which will tell thee, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16. 15. <hi>Act.</hi> 2, 5, 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.18. Whether this be my Lye or the Scriptures ſpeaking, let the hearers Judge, as alſo who is the Lyer, whether I for alledging plain, Teſtimonies of Scriptures, or thou for delivering my Anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, otherwiſe then thou receiveſt it, may not Millions of Men and Women, ſaieſt thou, who dwell in thoſe parts of the world, not coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſtendom wittneſs againſt thee: if an <hi>Egyptian</hi> miſt had not blinded thee, thou couldſt not have been ſo beſotted as to back thy Lye with thoſe places of the Letter, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.15. Which in effect prove Chriſts Command to his Diſciples, when they were upon earth, to go preach the glad tydings of the Goſpel to the generations they lived in.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119118:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Couldſt thou fetch thoſe Millions thou ſpeakeſt of for thy defence, yet could they not witneſs againſt me, the Word of the Lord is a ſure witneſs againſt thee, and all oppoſers of the univerſal precah<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of faith, or ſound of the Goſpel of Chriſt in all the world, and to every creature, therefore as formerly, ſo I ſay now, as the Apoſtle doth demand, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.18. <hi>Have they not all heard, but they have not all obeyed, as verſe</hi> the 16. Therefore thoſe Milions which thou ſaieſt are not counted Chriſtians, if they be not Chriſtians, 'tis not becauſe they have not heard, but becauſe they have not obeyed; read <hi>Act.</hi> 1.8. and <hi>Luke.</hi> 24.27. Which tells thee, the Apoſtles ſhall be witneſſes of Chriſt Jeſus to the uttermoſt part of the earth, and that repentance and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins ſhould be preached to all Nations. Now let all who have ears to hear, judge whether an <hi>Egyptian</hi> miſt and beſottedneſs be not rather in thy ſelf, to aledge theſe whom thou never ſaweſt, or heard, (but by the report of others, to be thy witneſs againſt me, and the Scriptures. There is two many nearor hand, who if their non obedience muſt witneſs againſt the Scriptures, that they have not heard the preaching of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles do witneſs fully, of which namely <hi>Martin Maſon</hi> is one, who is too full of fury, and wrath againſt the preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, to yeild obedience thereunto.</p>
            <p>Thy ſaying that <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.15. In effect proves Chriſt command to his Diſciples, when they were on earth, to go preach the glad tydings of the Goſpel to the generation they lived in: Dothplain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew, how deſirous thou art to out ſhort the Commiſſion of Chriſt, and ſtop the mouths of his Apoſtles, in their preaching by that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in theſe times; whoſe power and promiſe with that Commiſſion, as it was to all the world, and every creature, ſo it is to the worlds end, as is manifeſted in the Scriptures, <hi>verſe</hi> the 20.</p>
            <p>By which is diſcovered what relation thou haſt to Chriſt, or love, or aquaintance with his truth; If thou dideſt know Chriſt, <hi>as the truth is in Jeſus,</hi> thou wouldſt know, that though the Apoſtles be not perſonaly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, yet their word by which beleif in Chriſt is wrought, <hi>John.</hi> 47.20. and by which the world ſhall be judged, <hi>John.</hi> 12, 48. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16. and by which the word of God is manifeſt, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.3. and which is a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to all Nations through the whole world, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.14. yet remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, notwithſtanding thine and Millions of oppoſers, and denyers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And thus that <hi>Egypian</hi> miſt and ſottiſhneſs which thou ſaieſt is in me, is manifeſted in thy ſelf, who as thou goeſt about by <hi>London</hi> way to ſpeak with me, who lives by thee in <hi>Lincolne,</hi> ſo thou runeſt to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianed world (as thou calleſt them) who live many thouſands of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119118:6"/>Myles from thee, to be thy witneſs againſt me, that the Goſpel is not preached by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and againſt the Scriptures alſo: And our own knowledge, who have their preaching ſounding in our ears continually. Would any but a miſted blind man, bring a candle to witneſs againſt the Light of the Sun. Thy confuſion is further ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted: In thy acknowledging the Scriptures, in effect proves Chriſt command to his Diſciples, to go preach the glad tydings of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel: For thou denyſt, and oppoſeſt, that Chriſt which they preached, and alſo in his Ordinances, and therefore moſt miſerable is thy condition in that, to acknowledge it the Command of Chriſt, and the glad tydings of the Goſpel, and yet fight againſt it.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaieſt thou never queſtionedſt Chriſts Comiſſion, or their executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, yet thou thy ſelf denyſt obedience thereunto, and wouldeſt bring Millions of non Chriſtians, to witneſs againſt it, what greater queſtion can be againſt that Commiſtion to all the world, and every Creature in the world, or the execution thereof, then to ſay Millions of people in the world, have never heard of that Chriſt. Thou bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt me ſee my fooliſhneſs, and be aſhamed, but if that blend, which befottes all ſences that oppoſe the Truth, were not it thee, thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſee thy ſelf amongſt theſe Owls, and Batts, whoſe nightly noyſe is heard in the ruines of <hi>Babylon.</hi> But that wine being in thee, 'tis hid from thy Eyes.</p>
            <p>Thou repeateſt thy queſtion, How is the Goſpel preached to every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture under Heaven, if not by the Principal of light in the Conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> And I anſwer thee again, In the preaching of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, which worketh the principle of light in the Conſcience, <hi>which is the light of Chriſt, that lighteth every man that cometh into the World.</hi> And whatſoever pretended light in the Conſcience, that is not enlightned from thence, and leads not to the obedience of that preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 'tis darkneſs and not light, it is two ſecret and deſart, for the Saints and Diſeiples of Chriſt to go out to it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.26. and lead but where the fooliſh Woman brings her dead gueſts, <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.18.</p>
            <p>Take away thy Letter (ſaieſt thou) and by this mans Doctrine, there would be no principal of light, ariſing in thy Conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Take away the preaching of Chriſt in the Scriptures, which thou calleſt dead Letter, &amp; there would be the ſame in the Conſcience in relation to light, that would be in thy tongue, for hadeſt thou not their ſpeakings to ſtill thy mouth with what Name of Chriſt, or Spirit, or Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual weapon; or Goſpel; or Conſcience, or Light it ſelf wouldſt thou have: all that hear thee knows that thou haſt none of theſe expreſſions but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119118:6"/>from thence. Thoſe who ſpake by thy Spirit, when Chriſt was perſonally upon earth, might likewiſe ſay, take away this Carpinter, <hi>Marys</hi> Son, and there is no Meſias or Son of God, or Light and Saviour of the world; for as they contemned and deſpiſed Chriſt Jeſus, becauſe of his ſeeming meanneſs or outward manly eſtate, ſo thou doſt contemne and diſpiſe his Word, therefore his Word ſhall judge the in the lay day, <hi>John.</hi> 12.48. Shall men deſpiſe the way and means that God hath given, for teaching and correcting in righteouſneſs, and which is able to make men wiſe unto Salvation, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16, 17. Becauſe 'tis brought home to them in words and writing, ſuch diſpiſers ſhall wonder, and vaniſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way at the beholding the work of God by that which they ſo diſpiſe. <hi>Martin</hi> take this further with thee, to conſider of in way of anſwer, that whoſoever takes away, or denys that which thou calleſt dead Letter, ſhall find no light of Conſcience but what leads to diſtruction, the Scriptures are either the voyce or ſpeaking of God, or nothing, or worſe, if they be nothing or worſe, why doſt thou ſometimes ſay thou ownſt them, or why doſt thou ſpeak by them, and ſteal their word to fill thy mouth with and aledge them? And if they be the voyce and ſpeaking of God (as even they are) thou that wouldeſt take them away and calleſt them Dead and Life-leſs, wouldſt take away the voyce and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God and call it Dead and Life-leſs, and ſo art a plain oppoſer and ſet enemy againſt God, which manifeſteth thy dead and dark mind. Thy ſwelling words againſt me of groſs darkneſs, and calling me <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonian,</hi> and Lyer, and ſhame cover thy face, and the like, I ſlight them as Big words of wrath, for want of matter.</p>
            <p>Thou askeſt me, If there was not a Principal of Light in people before <hi>Moſes</hi> writ the Letter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There was the preaching of the Goſpel, the word of Faith which is the ſure Principle of Light, before <hi>Moſes</hi> writ the Letter, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>Abels</hi> offering, and <hi>Abrahams</hi> believing, compared with <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.8. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.4. As alſo the preaching of the Goſpel, or righteouſneſs by <hi>Noah,</hi> to the world of the ungodly, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. Yet Chriſt ſends the People to <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> to hear them, who did not only declare the Sacrifice, Circumciſion and Ceremonyes of the Law, but alſo the Faith and acceptance with God of theſe who before the Law, and in the Law did hear and obey the Goſpel of Faith; and ſaith Chriſt, if they will not hear them, they will not be perſwaded, though one ariſe from the dead; <hi>Luke.</hi> 16.29, 31. even ſo now, the people have Chriſt and the Apoſtles, if they will not hear them, no other dead ariſing light can perſwade them to hear the Goſpel of Faith: therefore what is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119118:7"/>of light before <hi>Moſes</hi> writ the Letter, to thy denyal of the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the Scriptures. <hi>Cornelius</hi> had as much light as thou canſt aledge, yet he muſt hear the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> for Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Thou telleſt me, I ſay in my Prayer, that the ſound of accuſing, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing, is in all conſciences: then it muſt needs be (ſaiſt thou) in the conſcience of Millions of people, that never heard of the preaching of repentance, and faith by the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That which I ſaid in my Paper, was that their Sound (ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Apoſtles) of accuſing or excuſing is in all conſciences, then ſaieſt thou, it muſt needs be in the conſcience of Millions, that never heard their ſound, but how this is agreeable with right reaſon, that the ſound of the Apoſtle preaching, muſt needs be in the conſciences of Millions, that never heard of their ſound, let the hearers Judge; yet let this be obſerved how thou ſtraineſt thy ſelf to ſhuffel out the Apoſtle and ſayſt in thy own pretended Light, leaving out my word, their ſound, applyed to the Apoſtles, and puteſt in thy word, the ſound, applyed to thy dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and then ſaieſt, I ſaid it; which is falſe in a double manner, both in leaving out what I ſaid, and ſaying what I ſaid not, if thou ſee not this to be a deceitful ſottiſhneſs, the ſtanders by will, this is like thy Logick in thy former Paper, which thou touldſt me came from the Rock of Ages: I asked thee in my former Paper, where thou, or any of thoſe who run abroad, now in theſe dayes, have come where Chriſt and his Apoſtles have not been before you. And to that I joyned my ſaying that the ſound of accuſing or excuſing is in all conſciences, all which thou haſt left out in 'its order and place, and without anſwer, that thou mayſt with more eaſe, perſwade others againſt the truth delivered by me; but they are weak diſcerners that ſeeth not what thou art in ſuch falſe deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>This thou calleſt my ſcornful queſtion, &amp; for want of anſwer, openeſt thy mouth in curſing, throwing out ſome of thy waters of bitterneſs which flow within; And after a terrible fit, thou art forced to ſay thou owneſt no other Goſpel but what the Apoſtles preached.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which I anſwer, that then thou muſt diſcern that which thou calleſt the light of the conſcience, for the Apoſtles never preached ſo, and then thou muſt own the man Chriſt Jeſus, who ſuffered at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> to be the Saviour of the world, and the Baptiſme with water up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on repentance, and Faith to be a Goſpel Ordinance, for this is that which the Apoſtles preached, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.10, and 3, 16, and 5, 30, 31, and 9, 34, and 13, 32, 38, 39, and 16, 30, 31, and 2, 38. Thus out of thy own mouth, thou art condemned for thy diſobedience.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119118:7"/>
            <p>Thou ſayeſt, you do not direct the people to any other thing then the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> did, that ſure word of Propheſie, the light in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to which they do well if theyake heed 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Then you muſt ſend them to the Scriptures or Propheſies of old, for ſo did the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> in the text, as the following verſos do witneſs, if thou have ears to hear, and to the Baptiſme of Repentance, for ſo did <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 2.38. which thou denyeſt and therefore ſpeakeſt falſely, in ſaying you direct the people as <hi>Peter</hi> did. <hi>Peter</hi> did not ſend or direct the people to the light in their own conſciences (as thou ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt he did) in that alſo thou ſpeakeſt falſely, and addeſt them words to the text, by which thou manifeſteth how blind &amp; bould oppoſer thou art, though God threatens his plagues againſt thee; for it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18. thou and thy generation do in this as all Antichriſtians have done, to make their own Idols ſtand up, thruſt in their own inventions amongſt the ſpeaking of the Spirit of God in the Scripture, but it will fall as <hi>Dagon</hi> did before the Ark.</p>
            <p>Alſo thou ſayeſt, you ſend them to the ſeed of the woman, the word of God, the unction, or, Chriſt within.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> You ſend them ſeveral wayes, it ſeems as pleaſeth the fancy of the ſender; but thou ſpeakeſt falſely, and intendeſt deceitfully, for all your ſending is to keep people from the knowledg of the womans ſeed, the word of God, the unction, or, Chriſt within. For the ſeed of the woman or of promiſe, is the man Chriſt, who was begotten and born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and ſo was he the womans ſeed, and he who brake the Serpents head, and looſſed the works of the Devil, by his death, and blood-ſhedin that fleſh, in which he came and dwelt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men; and the unction, or, Chriſt within, is the Spirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs ſent from Chriſt, into thoſe who believe in him, <hi>John</hi> 16.7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 29.20. But thy womans ſeed, and thy Chriſt within, and unction, or word, is thy faigned light which thou telleſt people, is in all conſciences, though in the ſtate of unbelief, or unregenerate, and thither wouldeſt thou ſend people, to ſeek Chriſt in their own dark hearts, and falſe ſpeakings in the deſart ſecret place, that ſo they may leave looking for the light of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to follow your matters contrary to Scriptures teaching, or the Apoſtles direction. But he cannot find Chriſt within, who denyeth Chriſt without, he cannot have Chriſt ſpiritually by faith, who denys Chriſt bodily raiſed from the grave, and aſcended, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in the Heavens. Thou and thy generation, are in that deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al manifeſted to be buſie ſticklers both againſt that Chriſt and the preaching of his Apoſtles; who preached Chriſt to thoſe in whom he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119118:8"/>was not, that they by faith might receive him, and that is the promiſe of unction, which only Saints deny as the earneſt of their everlaſting inheritance. And ſo he dwelleth in Saints, not in unbelievers, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13, 14. and 2.12, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. Therefore thine and thy fellows telling men that are not in the faith, they muſt look to the light anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Chriſt within them. As it is a ſmoak ariſing from below, to cover mens eyes from the light of the Son; ſo there is in its two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious evils, the one is, it ſtayes men from following Chriſt, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour whoſe power, excellency, and glorious manifeſtation of love is ſounded forth, and made known by the ſpirit of God in the Scriptures, to bring all men to everlaſting life through faith in him. The other evil is, it makes men liſten to the falſe imaginations, and deceitful perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of their own hearts, which hath been the cauſe of all Idolatry, ſuperſtition, and diſobedience to the Law of faith, that hath been; for men leaving the ſpiritual teaching, and commands of Chriſt in the Scripture, and following their own Invenſions, and heart Imaginations run themſelves into ſeveral falſe practiſes, and bould diſobedience, of which this of yours is not the leaſt, for the greater pretence of light (in diſobedience) the greater evil.</p>
            <p>And this bouldneſs of thy heart, by following its Imaginations is further manifeſted, in thy ſaying, how ſhould the ſeed of the woman break the Serpents head, if the ſeed of the woman, the unction, or; Chriſt within, and the ſeed of the Serpent, the man of ſin, be not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
            <p>By which all may plainly ſee who are in the light, thy denyal of the death of Chriſt, who by his death and blood-ſhed in that once ſuffering at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> did break the Serpents head according to Gods decree, and appointment: but thou in denyal of that, and to give him a plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, for his his broken head, telleſt the world or unbelievers, that their light within (which is their heart imaginations and vain fancies) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that which is preached by Chriſt, and his Apoſtles to give light, is the ſeed of the woman that breaks the Serpents head, no other break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his head wouldeſt thou have them to believe, and thus wouldeſt thou if thou could ſave the breaking of the ſepents head, and give him a hellmet rather.</p>
            <p>Thou runeſt on with a many words, ſome ſtollen from Scripture, and ſome thy own Imagination, and to conclude, what ſayeſt, but this is a myſtery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which I anſwer, 'tis a myſtery indeed, but it is the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Iniquity, for it denyeth Chriſt Jeſus, and ſetteth up falſe devices
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119118:8"/>in his room, but the righteous deſires not to know the deepneſs of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan as thou ſpeaks in thy former paper, thou ſaiſt to me, poor man how hath thy father befooled thee, hath not the God of this world blinded thy mind 'tis ſo or elſe thou wouldſt ſee thy nakedneſs, and be aſhamed of thy ignorance, with more ſuch big words,</p>
            <p>And this was becauſe, I had ſaid, the light of Chriſt is manifeſted, by the preaching of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, hearing, and receiving, of which ſaid I, is the inlet to the Spirit of promiſe, and for proof I alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Acts.</hi> 2.38, the truth of which thou not being able to gainſay, ſmiteſt me thus with thy tongue for reveng in thy offence at truth, but when thy paſſion was ſomewhat over, and thou hadſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got why thou waſt angry, thou ſaidſt the very ſame thy ſelf which thou condemneſt in me, thy words were theſe, Did not the <hi>Galatians</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Spirit, by the hearing of faith, that is (ſayſt thou) by believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that Chriſt, which <hi>Paul</hi> preached? alſo thou ſaidſt, that is the word of faith which we preach, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> and hearing of the word of faith, (the light in the conſcience) is the inlet to the Spirit of promiſe.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to all which I ſaid, what cauſe haſt thou thus to complain againſt me, when thou art forced to ſay the ſame thing with me, thou haſt in this diſarmed thy ſelf, and yeilded the victory, 'tis in vain for thee to take up for another charg.</p>
            <p>Let the wiſe Reader now judge, if there were not juſt cauſe for thee to lay thy hand upon thy mouth in ſilence, or confeſs thy folly, for exclaming againſt me, for ſaying what the Scripture ſaith, when thou ſayeſt the very ſame with me, and with the text of Scripture alledged; ſave only thy addition, the light in the conſcience, which is to be thrown to thee, being thy own Idol, and not belonging to the text. But thou for want of a gracious humbled Spirit, to acknowledg the truth, when it is ſo plainly laid before thee: continueſt thy old corrupt language, like <hi>Balaam</hi> to curſe where thou knoweth the Lord hath bleſſed, but thy mouth is ordered contrary to the deſires of thy heart.</p>
            <p>Be it remembred (ſaiſt thou) that thou haſt owned the light of the conſcience, to be the inlet to the Spirit of promiſe.</p>
            <p>There is no cauſe <hi>(Martin)</hi> to forget that, being remembred that thou ſayeſt with me, that light is by the hearing of faith preached by the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Then in thy former paper, touldſt me of Juggling, the which I called upon thee to prove, but thou not being able, returneſt to ask me, if I have not ſaved thee ſome labour, and done it my ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. Martin,</hi> this is juſt like thee, to ſhew ſo little cauſe for ſo
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119118:9"/>large accuſation, thy labour hath been great enough, were it known to prove that thou cannot; but I will ſhew how with male labour, I have opened <hi>Martin Maſons</hi> Juggling Box, who cried condemnation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me for that which I found he himſelf had, and I alſo found that when he had called the people together, pretending to ſhew them Chriſt the Saviour, and light and truth, there I diſcovered all to be nothing but a crucifix, and falſe fained lights, and tryfels of ſelf-dinying.</p>
            <p>Thou mayſt have ſpared the labour of telling me, I one while own the Letter, to be the inlet to the Spirit of promiſe, and another time own the light of the Conſcience to be the inlet, ſometime calling the Letter, ſometime the Spirit, the Rule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For I never owned to thee, any light of Conſcience but that which is the preaching of Faith in the Scriptures: which Light or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning, thy ſelf hath before owned (though fore againſt thy will) and for thy pretended light, that hath not 'its original from that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preaching power of the Apoſtles, I deny it as a deadly darkneſs: where haſt thou that word Letter from me, calling it the inlet, or rule, is it not a word of thy own diviſing againſt the Apoſtles preaching, or to uſe thy own termes, a Brat of thy own begetting, why wilt thou father it upon me, charge it not upon me, but chalenge thy own.</p>
            <p>Is not thy foundation (ſaiſt thou) built upon the Letter, doſt not thou account, that for the word of God Which <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Petter</hi> preache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I do account that for the Word of God which <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> preached, and I am built upon that foundation which they have laid, which is Chriſt Jeſus, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10, 11. And this is denyed by none but the raiging Heathen, and diſobedient denyers of Chriſt, to be come in the fleſh, the Apoſtles <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Theſſelonians</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. <hi>For this cauſe alſo thank we God without ceaſing, that when ye received of us the word of the preaching of God, ye received it not as the word of men, but as it is indeed, the word of God, which alſo worketh in you that believe:</hi> let this be compared with thy denyal of that to be the word of God which <hi>Paul</hi> preached; and thoſe who hear thee, will account thee as <hi>Paul</hi> wileth, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8. Art thou not by this proved one of thoſe, who would move men away from, and pevert the Goſpel of Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.6, 7. May not I juſtly ſay of thee, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of thy Brother <hi>Alexander</hi> the Copper-Smith, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14, 15. <hi>The Load reward thee according to thy works,</hi> and let all men bewar of thee, and all ſuch, for you withſtand the Apoſtles preaching ſore, 'tis well thou art no wiſer in thy evils, but to deſtroy thy worke with thy own hands, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119118:9"/>let thy blindneſs in wickedneſs to appear to all men, not only in this thy groſs denyal of the plain truth, but in thy ſometimes acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which thou hear denyeſt to cover thy deceit with; but layeſt it the more open to the view of all men. As for example, thou owneſt (to deceive by) Chriſt to be the word of God, and thou ſaiſt in thy paper to me, that <hi>Paul</hi> Preached Chriſt; and now forgetting that, thou wouldſt deny that to be the word of God which <hi>Paul</hi> Preached; if he that biddeth me in thy laſt paper ſee my ſottiſhneſs, and be aſhamed, would make right application of this to himſelf, he would ſee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but howſoever the ſtanders by will: doth not the Scripture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly declare that the Apoſtle preached the word of God, as <hi>Acts</hi> 17.13. and 8.25. and 13.5. And they preached Chriſt, (whom thou ſayeſt thou owneſt to be the word of God) waſt thou clapt up in ſome clouded darkneſs, and oblivion, when thou writ this, ſurely this madneſs will appear to all men.</p>
            <p>Thou takeſt occaſion at my ſpeaking of the Apoſtles preaching the word of God, and Jeſus; to ask me if the word of God, and Jeſus be two diſtinct things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If to fill paper, thou didſt not love to make frivilous queſtions, thou would not thus ſpend thy ſelf and time, look in thy former paper, &amp; thou may find this ſaying firſt from thy ſelf, quoting <hi>Acts</hi> 17.13, 18. where 'tis ſaid <hi>Paul</hi> preached the word of God, and that he preached Jeſus theſe Scriptures, would ſatisfie thee (if thou wert not as I have told thee) that preaching the word of God, and preaching Jeſus, is all one, and that my accounaing, that for the word of God which <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> preached, is an account agreeable to the Scriptures, and not againſt any but thoſe who are againſt the truth.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaiſt in thy former paper, that my fancy is found to be built upon the ſandy foundation of litteral printed leaves, not the rock, yet (ſaith thou) that which gave forth the leaves I own.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that then thou muſt own the Printer, for he gave forth the leaves, and ſo thy own foundation by thy own confeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt needs be Sandy; of which without proof or my confeſſion thou haſt accuſed me, I own not, or am built upon any ſuch foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (ſaid I) or upon <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Peter,</hi> but that which I am built upon, is that ſpiritual, and powerful word ſounded and preached forth by the Apoſtles, either in word or writing: at which anſwer thou art ſo nettled, and ſtickles, and ſtiſlles up and down, and yet for all the ſtir thou makes, thou cannot free thy ſelf, thou calleſt to thy friends to ſee me put to my ſhifts; but they that are friends indeed, will tell thee
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119118:10"/>thou art put to thy ſhifts with a witneſs, for thou haſt no defence for thy ſelf therein, but as ſcoulds have one againſt another, which is to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe a foul tongue, calling me lyer again and again, and high flown Phariſee, and the like, but in the middeſt of all thy coller buſling to free thy ſelf, thou haſt ſunck thy ſelf further in, for now thou art forced to confeſs that the pure ſpirit of the living God gave forth the letter, and yet thou calls it dead letter, and in thy title page thou ſaiſt thou art a miniſter, not of the letter; and in thy foregoing page thou telleſt me I cry up the letter; now call thy friends and let them ſee who will be put to their ſhifts, to free thy ſelf of being a blaſphemer, in ſaying that which thou confeſſeth to be given forth by the pure ſpirit of the living God, is a dead thing; and of being a Miniſter of Antichriſt, in ſaying thou art no Miniſter, but a cryer down of that which is given forth by the pure Spirit of the living God, by thy own confeſſion: ſee what evil contradictions and obfurdities thou haſt run thy ſelf into, as all do who take up arms againſt the truth.</p>
            <p>Thou telleſt me in the next place I am puzled, and tormented, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in thy paper thou cryeſt not up the letter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thy friends will tell thee thou art more puzled and tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in crying it down, who in thy ſtrugling to cry it down, and againſt that which thou acknowledgeth, to be given forth by the pure Spirit of the living God, art thy ſelf thrown down headlond, ſo far from the ſtate of a faithful Miniſter, of the everlaſting Goſpel, (as thou call'ſt thy ſelf) that thou neither ſheweth grace, or good intelligence, and art neither Prophet, or the Son of a Prophet, but as men have taught thee from thy youth, ſo doſt thou remain in low place amongſt the heards-men, where thy friend looking upon thee, will ſee who is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted, and ſorely wounded; boaſting brave doth ſeldome conquer, but the truth will overcome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou askeſt why the Heathen rage, and the men imagin a vain thing; 'tis mens offence at Chriſt Jeſus, againſt whom they band themſelves, and aſſemble together, Warring againſt, the Lord, and his anoynted, witneſs, <hi>Martin Maſon,</hi> and his fellows, whoſe raging words, and not without blaſphemie, and vain Imaginations, is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to all who have eyes to ſee, or ears to hear.</p>
            <p>I ſaid in my former paper, that the baptiſme of repentance, hearing of faith preached, and believing, is the inlet to the Spirit of promiſe, as theſe Scriptures teſtifie, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.36. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2.</p>
            <p>Thou telleſt this to the world, as matter againſt me, but leaves out the Scripture that I brought to witneſs it by; by which thy falſhood
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119118:10"/>and deceit is laid open; for thou leaves them out, knowing what thou accuſeth me of reacheth them, but they will ſpeak to thy ſhame, and confound thee before all men. Thou being empty of any anſwer thereto, ſaiſt, by this mans Doctrine none have the ſpirit of promiſe that bow not to his Sprinkling.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. Martin,</hi> I have not at any time called upon thee, or any to how to any Sprinkling, neither have I uſed the word Sprinkling to thee upon any ſuch account, 'tis a word brought only by thy ſelf for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, when thou wanteſt an anſwer: in which thou doſt but ſhew how thou runneſt into holes, and Caves of thy own digging and ſcratch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to hide thee from the preſence of truth.</p>
            <p>If I ſhould ſay to thee for want of other anſwer, when thou telleſt of the light within, to be the inlet to the Spirit, without the Scriptures teaching; that by this mans doctrine none have the Spirit that how not to his quaking, wouldſt thou not call me Lyer, and deal me a many foul words for it; let that charity now begin at home, and deal ſuch words rightly where they do belong, would any but one who is blind in heart, publiſh himſelf in print in ſuch poor pettiſh ſpirited things as thou doſt, I am aſhamed to have to do with ſuch ſilly ſtuffe, neither would I, but that I knew my ſilence would make thee boaſt and be wiſe in thy own concent, therefore I chuſe rather to anſwer thee as I am ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.5. Thou bids <hi>Jonathan</hi> tell thee, if he did not a little before own the light of the conſcience to be the inlet of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. Jonathan</hi> by writing hath told <hi>Martin</hi> before, and tells him now that he diſ-owns his falſe fained light; but he owns the light of the conſcience, enlightned by the preaching of faith according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Thou askeſt me if I will be a Lyer, whether thou wilt or no: as though thou had the making, and diſpoſing of Lyes, as a Child be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Father of Lyes: but though thy will like thy Fathers, be to have all Lyers like thy ſelf, yet thou muſt want of thy will in me, for I neither love or make Lyes, neither canſt thou prove any Lye againſt me, though thou call me Lyer, but it is a ſmall matter to find a Lye in a foul mouth.</p>
            <p>I am willing to refer what is ſaid to the wiſe in heart to judge, who is the Babler and bond-ſlave in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and ſayes, and unſayes: which is the eſteeme thou would have me in with thoſe to whom thou publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſo againſt me, and whom thou askeſt if I do not place water, and beleeving in the Letter in the room of Chriſt, by making them the way, and the door or inlet to the Spirit of promiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It would agree better with right reaſon, if thou ſhewed where
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119118:11"/>I ſaid ſo, leaſt they that find not any ſuch ſaying of mine, muſt needs ſay thou art a Lyer whether they will or no; I deny, thou haſt them words from me; water adminiſtred upon repentance and faith in Chriſt Jeſus. I would have where it ſhould be according to Goſpel teaching, that is the Baptiſme of repentance, which I have ſo much ſpoken to thee, and againſt which thou and thy generation deviſeth ſo many croſs oppoſings, to wind out and ſhroud your ſelves from the appearance of truth, but your coverings are too ſcant, which makes your nakedneſs be ſeen of every paſſer by.</p>
            <p>Who ever (ſaiſt thou) are not Spiritually blind, will ſee the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy of the beaſt, for Chriſt the light of the world is the door and the way, <hi>John</hi> 10.9, and 14.16. and ſo the inlet to the Spirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Doth Chriſt being the door and the way to Salvation, deny faith to be the inlet of his ſpirit of promiſe, is not entrance into Chriſt the door by faith, and is not receiving the Spirit of promiſe by faith: then faith in Chriſt is the inlet to Salvation, and the inlet of the ſpirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe into the heart therefore, though Chriſt be the door and the way.</p>
            <p>Yet thoſe who have not but denies faith in Chriſt Jeſus, have no inlet or entrance therein; then ſurely thou muſt needs be without Chriſt, and hath no entrance into him, calling it the blaſphemy of a beaſt, to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the plain Teſtimony of Chriſt to prove faith to be the inlet of the Spirit of promiſe, ſurely all that hear thee, will ſee thy ſpiritual blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in ſuch faith-leſs, grace-leſs deliveries. Thou askeſt me where the Creature muſt look for Chriſt if not within.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Creature muſt look for Chriſt, as he doth openly manifeſt himſelf to every Creature according to the Scriptures, thou nor any other are not like to find him within in your faithleſs condition, till you hear the Scriptures direction, and obey the teaching of Chriſt therein, and ſo become new Creatures according to the Goſpel, for none but new Creatures have Chriſt within them, and no new Creatures in the denyal of the Baptiſme of repentance; the denyal of which is manifeſted in thee, in thy hot words of contempt againſt it: being thy ſelf ſo fouled in foul water without repentance, even ſince thou received thy Romiſh waſhing, and not puriſyed from that by the lavour of regeneration, remains in thy old unclean condition, not obeying the truth thy ſelf, but railng upon thoſe that do.</p>
            <p>And though Chriſt ſtand at thy door and knock, and call upon thee to open thy door, and amend thy life and be Baptized in the Name of Chriſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119118:11"/>Jeſus for remiſſion of thy ſins, yet thou wilt not hear him and open thy door to receive him; but haſt received a ſtranger called falſe Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; who becauſe he acknowledgeth whoredom, and drunkenneſs, and murther is ſin, yet becauſe he tells thee not that diſobedience to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and teachings of Chriſt in reference to his Law of faith is ſin, is Spiritual Whoredome, and Drunkenneſs, and Murther, and Theft, and the like, therefore thou cryeſt out againſt the Ordinances of Chriſt to outface thy diſobedience thereunto: but if an evil Spirit ſhould not come with ſomething to deceive with, the poſſeſſed therewith muſt be a profeſſed Devil, in maintaining its Motion. But the man of ſin comes in all deceivableneſs of unrighteouſneſs, to perſwade thoſe who are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that they are Saints, when they are the quite contrary; and now to give our Audience a right knowledg of what we contend for, and the difference thereof, that ſo they may make right application of truth or falſhood, to which of us it belongs, let them know, That what I have declared and do contend for, is for the maintenance of the faith once given to the Saints according to the Scriptures, and preaching of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, which is the light and way of God, to direct all men to everlaſting life, as the Scriptures do plainly witneſs, <hi>John</hi> 14.6. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.9, 10. <hi>John</hi> 3.16. Thy declaration and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending is without, and denying the Scriptures, and preaching of the man Chriſt that dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for the ſins of the whole world, or the Apoſtles ſent of him: ſo thine is a thing in ſecret, not according to the open declared will and command of Chriſt or teaching of his, and therefore muſt needs be a deceit, and not to be received but accounted accurſed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9. <hi>John</hi> 9.10, 11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17.</p>
            <p>If I muſt receive thee as in the truth for ſaying, thou haſt a light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thee which thou calleſt Chriſt, when thou walkeſt contrary to, and denyeſt the declared will of Chriſt Jeſus in the Scriptures; then from the ſame ground I muſt receive another that ſaith ſo, and then the <hi>Pope</hi> and his Prelates, and theirs, or any ſuch who are as able to declare what they ſay they have of Chriſt within, as <hi>Martin Maſon,</hi> or any by whoſe hand held forth, he hath been led into this Condition, and they are for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe to be excepted againſt, but for their walking contrary to and denying the declared will of Chriſt Jeſus in the Scriptures, and following their own Inventions, which they call light: And of this <hi>Martin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and his fellows, do manifeſt themſelves to be as guilty as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and ſo with them denyers of Chriſt, to be come in the fleſh, for who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever are denyers of that Chriſt Jeſus who died at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for mans redemption, and his teachings, and commands given forth by him and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119118:12"/>his Apoſtles while they were perſonally upon Earth amongſt men; muſt needs be found guilty of the Apoſtle <hi>Johns</hi> brand upon them, 1 <hi>John</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3. 2 <hi>John</hi> 7. Your Evaſion of Chriſt coming in your fleſh will not cover your deceit, but more diſcovers your oppoſition to Chriſt Jeſus, for your telling men of Chriſt coming in their fleſh, or your fleſh, is to make them deny Chriſt come in his own fleſh, or the fleſh, which was the onely fleſh or body, that God came in to give his Law or Teſtament of faith to men, and was appointed to ſuffer and ſeal his Teſtament with his blood.</p>
            <p>Thou often talkeſt of the light within, telling men and women in ſecret, of every ſin they commit, yet thy light doth not tell thee or them of your ſins of unbelief againſt that Saviour, who tells thee in his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel that the world ſhall be condemned for ſin, becauſe they believe not in him; Thou wilt not open thy window to let this light of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhine into thy dark heart, but only light thy ſelf and others with the nightly Torches of your own kindling, which at the beſt let you but fee that evil, and that righteouſneſs, which is onely in relation to the Law of works, by which Law none ſhall be juſtified or condemned, thy light is a Popiſh light, and had its kindling from that fire, and not from the Alter Chriſt Jeſus; and therefore is a ſtrange fire, and ſo an abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from which fire hath been the kindling of mens minds, in way of merit by their own works, againſt the Juſtification that is by faith only, according to the Scriptures, in the maintaining of which faith in Chriſt Jeſus, many thouſand who have waſht their long robes, and made them white in the blood of the Lamb, and have not loved their lives unto the death, but have laid down their lives in witneſs of that truth, in which they have been ſuch overcomers, that one would think there ſhould have been no more riſing up of that beaten down falſhood in the accuſer of the Saints; yet here appears the ſame Spirit moving from below, which though it hath not the horns, and teeth, and clawes of the beaſt, to kill and rend the Saints as the former did, yet it hath the mouth or voyce of the Dragon, to accuſe and curſe and ſmite with the tongue, thoſe who deny to receive their falſe devices, by which voyce thou calleſt it blalphemy in me, to ſay the Spirit is received by the hearing and receiving of faith preached, and ſo accuſeth the Apoſtles al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of blaſphemie, of whom I received it, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. becauſe it denies the Spirit is received by thy dark works.</p>
            <p>Thou biddeſt <hi>Jonathan</hi> tell thee, was the bearing of faith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2. hearing the Prophets and Apoſtles, or hearing that Chriſt which <hi>Paul</hi> preached, to be in all, Jew and Greek, <hi>Barbarian, Scithian,</hi> bond and free.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:119118:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If <hi>Martins</hi> eyes had a Chriſtian opening, he would ſee that either he muſt deny <hi>Paul</hi> to be an Apoſtle, and the Apoſtles to preach all one Chriſt, or ſay theſe are both one; and if <hi>Martin</hi> ſhould tell me that the Chriſt which <hi>Paul</hi> preached, and the Chriſt which <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> and others of the Apoſtles preached, was not all one Chriſt, all that hears him tell me ſo, will ſay he ſpeaks not truth, and for <hi>Barbarians, Scithians, &amp;c.</hi> the Apoſtle in that place names them not, and where he doth namethem, as in <hi>Col.</hi> 11. He doth not name them as having Chriſt without or before faith in him, but that as to the Jewes, ſo to all others Chriſt is the ſame, both in the offer of himſelf to all by his preaching, as alſo his indwelling with them in receiving him by faith, but neither in <hi>Col.</hi> 11. or any where elſe doth the Apoſtles preach Chriſt to be or dwell in any, either Jew or Greek, but by faith only, (quite contrary to your teaching) without which faith wrought by the Apoſtles preaching, thy pretended Chriſt unction and light within, is all vanity and deceit.</p>
            <p>Thou askeſt what ſhal be the condemnation of all man-kind, who never heard of the name of Chriſt at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> if not the light of Chriſt placed in the conſcience, and wherefore is the light of Jeſus left there in the heart of every man and woman, if not to lead men and women out of ſin into holineſs, and whether any thing without can redeem a Soul from ſin, but that Jeſus who is the light of the world, and ſhines in the conſcience of every man and woman in the world. Anſwer theſe queriers without any Serpentine evaſion, conjuring conſequence, or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian falicies, ſaiſt thou.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The condemnation of the condemned, ſhall be for not believing in the name of that Chriſt, who dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as the Scriptures lively and abundantly ſtand up to witneſs, though the dark generation calls them dead, <hi>John</hi> 16.8, 9. and 12.48. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Mark</hi> 25.41, 42, 48. And thy ſaying they have not heard of the Name of that Chriſt, that dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> is of no value, for it is but thy falſe witneſs in the maintenance of thy own evil cauſe, and therefore to be rejected, being a neggative, againſt the Scriptures affirmative, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thy own words (the light of Chriſt placed in the conſcience) is againſt thee, for how ſhall the conſcience be enlightned by Chriſt that never heard of him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14, 15. Here thou haſt Enſnared thy ſelf, now thou muſt either acknowledge with me, that the enlightning of all conſciences, is by the preaching of the faith in that Chriſt, who ſuffered for ſin at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or plainly deny him to be the Chriſt, whom thou denying art in ſin, as the ſame Chriſt tells thee, <hi>John</hi> 8.48.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119118:13"/>and till thou hear the voyceof that Chriſt who calls thee out of the State of ſin or unbelief, to believe in his Name, and waſh away thy ſins in his blood, thou art not in the State of Holineſs, but in uncleanneſs, what ever thy heart Imaginations and falſe fancy may ſooth thee up withall, for there is no State of cleanneſs, or holineſs ſpiritual, but by faith only in that Chriſt Jeſus, who ſuffered at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Which Chriſt Jeſus the light of the world in his ſufferings at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> did without them redeem Souls from ſins; thy Queries denying this doth manifeſt thy denyal of that Chriſt, who died for ſinners; whoſe redemption doth work faith and light in men, but not any thing in man doth work his redemption, for as formerly I have told thee and others of thy generation (at which you have been ſo wrathful, but never gave any anſwer) that redemption is the cauſe of mans belief, not belief the cauſe of mans redemption, for ſo ſhould men deny Chriſt, and be his own redeemer, but Chriſt is a redeemer before man be a believer, for what ſhould man believe if not redemption, and who ſhould he believe if not the redeemer. As a man cannot own Chriſt the Saviour, and deny his redemption, ſo a man cannot own redemption and deny the Saviour. But thy Queries plainly teſtify thee to be a denyer of both.</p>
            <p>In the next place, thou haſt broken (in thy blindneſs) thy fore-head againſt a rock, that lay full in thy way, for thou art forced to confeſs, that I ſay ſomething to the proof of Baptiſme of Repentance, in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.59. If I, and my freinds, can witneſs ſuch a condition as thoſe convicts did in the four laſt verſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> My freinds and I, witneſſing the condition required, verſe the 38. do manifeſt converſion which is more then conviction, which converſion doth not only witneſs by the gift promiſed thereunto, that condition in the four laſt verſes upon the like, or any Goſpel occaſion requiring; but the condition, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.59, 60. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. For my freinds, and I, do witneſs againſt thee, and all who deny to follow Chriſt in the Regeneration, or Baptiſme of Repentance, that if we follow not that converſion to do as Goſpel need requireth, to the loſs of what we here enjoy, and life and all, if we be thereunto called, for Chriſt and his Goſpel ſake, we violate our Baptiſme and deſtroy our faith: but to leave any of theſe, and not for the Goſpel ſake, or it requiring and calling thereunto, but preſently from an idle notion to ſeem to have what is not within, 'tis a denyal of faith, and is hypocriſie; turn thy eyes to thoſe of thy own generation, and ſee if thou can ſpie none who are ſo far from parting from their own eſtates, that although convinced, yet are not converted to reſtore that which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119118:13"/>others complain againſt them for; as taken from them, by Exaction and Violence, while garments will not cover Extortion, the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the Saints is the cloathing of the regeneration. If my freinds and I could not witneſs the condition of the four laſt verſes; or, the 38. verſe (of which thou canſt not accuſe us in a Goſpel language) is it right therefore for thee to deny Baptiſme, call the wiſe in heart to Judge, if this be from a conſcience rightly enlightened: and they will tell thee, that rather thou ought to ſtand up in the right uſe and practice thereof, according to its faithful inſtitution, and not deny Baptiſme becauſe others who profeſs it, are not rightly qualified for it: and when the Hypocrite hath caſt out the beam in his own eye, he will ſee more clearly any mote that is in ours: till when if thou make uſe of thy own words (let the babler be ſilent) it will be more wiſedome, and that lying pride and paſſion, which here and ſo often thou would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the world of againſt me, would not ſo plainly appear in thy ſelf, and then blindly boldly, callit perfection.</p>
            <p>Thou telleſt me, water ſprinkling is not once named there, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.32. To which I anſwer, that neither would it be named here, but that thy low light looks thee out that bubble to prevent thy obedience to that baptiſme which is named there; after thy forced confeſſion of the truth thereof as afore is manifeſted: and for a further occaſion againſt that truth, thou askeſt me if Chriſts Baptiſme conſiſt of outward water. I anſwer, if it did, <hi>Martin Maſon</hi> were a Baptized man, for he hath had outward water; but wanting in ward repentance, and faith in that Chriſt, whoſe ordinance Baptiſme is, therefore he is not Baptiſed but denyeth that council of God againſt himſelf, as his predeceſſors in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyal thereof did, <hi>Luke</hi> 7. I alſo will ask thee a queſtion, whoſe Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme was it that <hi>Philip</hi> Baptized the <hi>Eunuch</hi> with, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.38. And that <hi>Peter</hi> commanded <hi>Cornelius</hi> to be Baptized with, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.47, 48. If thou acknowledg it Chriſts Baptiſme, thy fable is anſwered; If thou ſay it was not Chriſts Baptiſme, whoſe ſeavants were they in the doing, and commanding it to be done; lay by thy lewd language, and let me have an anſwer to this, who never receiveſt anſwer from thee yet to any thing that I deſired an anſwer to, in meekneſs, and modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but in unreaſonable railings; and when thou knoweſt what the Baptiſme of repentance is, by a right converſion wrought in thy ſelf, thou wilt know what it is to ſuffer with Chriſt, and what the Baptiſme of the holy Ghoſt is, till when the Serpent that is ſo quick in thy mouth, ſtops it from confeſſion to Salvation.</p>
            <p>Thou ſhould anſwer, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13. Which thou calleſt my laſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119118:14"/>proof, and was brought to prove that the Spirit of promiſe is receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by believing, as alſo <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2. was alledged to prove the ſame; but thou having no mind to acknowledg the truth, though ſo plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing before thee, and wanting anſwer againſt it; asks me what was this word of truth, if not Jeſus the word of God, the ſure word of Propheſie which ſhined in the <hi>Epheſians</hi> dark hearts, which they knew not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Is there any thing in this (worthy to be called an anſwer) to defend thee in thy denyall of the Spirit, to be received by the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the faith preached, and believing the word of truth, and Jeſus the word of God being alone, the Apoſtles preached that word of truth, and Jeſus the word of God, to work faith in men, by which faith the Spirit of promiſe was received, what help for thee in this, but to throw thee backward: that word of truth, and Jeſus the word of God, did not ſhine in the <hi>Epheſians</hi> dark hearts, before the Apoſtles preached to them, as thou falſly and ignorantly would perſwade, but after the Apoſtles preaching they believed, and after they believed, they were ſealed with the holy Spirit of promiſe, as that text ſaith, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13. but thou thruſts away the word after, which the text delivers, that thy darkneſs might be placed before the Apoſtles preaching of Chriſt Jeſus, but Chriſt telleth thee, <hi>John</hi> the 10.8. that all ſuch fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comers, are thieves and robbers: compare this thy ſaying, with the ſure word of Propheſie which ſhined in their dark hearts, which they knew not; with what thou ſayeſt before, that the unction, the womans ſeed, the Chriſt within, is that light which is in all conſciences before faith, and without; &amp; before the Apoſtles preaching; ſo that by thy Doctrine, the Apoſtle preaching the word of truth; or, Jeſus the word of God, brought nothing to the <hi>Epheſians</hi> but what they had before, for if they had the unction, the Chriſt within, which is the Spirit of promiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, then were they Sealed before; but the Apoſtle telleth them, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. that before they believed they were without Chriſt, ſo that I muſt either deny the <hi>Epheſians</hi> converſion by the Apoſtles preaching of faith, and the Apoſtles ſaying, that after they believed they were Sealed, and that before they were without Chriſt, and ſo make the Apoſtle a lyer, (which God forbid) or tell <hi>Martin Maſon</hi> he cannot eſcape be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the lyer, and therefore by the ſentence of his own mouth, muſt have his mouth ſtopped: a many foul and wicked words proceed from thee, in the next place, which I will leave to all who have learned to let their words be few, and gratious, to ſee by what Spirit thou art led? and to Judge whether ſuch expreſſions, (to avoyd anſwer) be the new tongue ſpeaking of a Saint, or ſpeaking like the Dragons.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:119118:14"/>
            <p>Thou asks me if I ſhame not to tell thee with my falſe tongue, that thou contemns the faith in the ſufferings of Chriſt,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I would thou wert repentantly aſhamed at thy contempt of the ſufferings of the Lord Chriſt, that dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> which contempt of thine is manifeſted in theſe words, in thy paper. But thou (ſpeaking to me) and the drunkard, and ſcum of the earth, who fed your ſelves with the meer froathy verbal faith in the ſufferings, of that ſingle man Chriſt Jeſus at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and yet wallow in your wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, are not ſaved or redeemed from your ſins. And in the ſame Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per alledged, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.2. Saiſt thou, did the Apoſtle here ſignifie, that every one that confeſſeth Chriſt come in the fleſh, of the ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> that every one confeſſing this is of God, why then the Pope will ſay he believes this?</p>
            <p>Now let the honeſt hearted in the Nation, whom thou calls upon to Judge, let them I ſay Judge, whether this language be not a contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous ſpeaking: Thou (as the manner of thy generation is) when thou calleth others to Judge, leaveth out that which thou knoweſt will moſt evidence thy contempt, as here, thou leaves out the word ſingle man, and ſingle perſon, which were thy words to me, but here thou leaves them out, and then calleſt to the wiſe in heart to Judge: will not thy light within, let thee ſee this to be falſhood and diſſimulation: Chriſt Jeſus was the Son of <hi>Mary</hi> according to the fleſh; but thy brethren who called him the <hi>Carpinter, Maries</hi> Son, <hi>Mar.</hi> 6.3. ſpeak that in deſpiſing contempt againſt him. So he was the Man Chriſt, and a perſon like unto us in all things ſave only ſin: but thy calling him ſingle man, and ſingle perſon, at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> is from the ſame ſpirit of deſpiſing contempt, as the honeſt hearted will tell thee. <hi>Martin</hi> thy light leading thee in wayes contrary to the way of faith, only in that Chriſt, that ſuffered at Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, leadeſt thee from the true and everlaſting light &amp; life, to the place of death &amp; darkneſs: for there is no life or light leading to Salvation, but by faith in that Chriſt only who ſuffered at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which thou plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doſt deny, and rageſt ſo againſt me for diſcovering thy flying to any, whoſe faith thou calleſt meerly froathy and verbal, will not help thee in thy denyal of faith to Salvation: for ſuch is no faith, the Scripture tells thee, there is one faith, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.5. which faith Juſtifieth &amp; ſaveth, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8. but whence haſt thou thy frothy verbal faith, that is the device of thy Spirit of deluſion, which as it would have many Chriſts to deny that one Chriſt who ſuffered at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſo it would have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny faiths, to deny that faith which is to Salvation, according to the Goſpel: thy telling me of wallowing in my wickedneſs with the drunk<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ards
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119118:15"/>, and ſcum of the earth, is but thy raging at rebuke, for thy bold Blaſphemie againſt the Lord that bought thee. Now Judge ſaiſt thou, O ye wiſe in heart; is the Scripture, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. call not him who ſuffered at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the man Chriſt Jeſus; and may not I uſe the language of the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The wiſe in heart, (are no formal <hi>Quakers</hi>) will tell thee thy language is quite contrary to that of the Apoſtles, for the Apoſtle in that Scripture, calls the man Chriſt Jeſus, the Mediatour betwixt God and man. But thou calls him the ſingle man, and ſingle perſon; in contempt of faith in him, and to make men deny his Mediatour-ſhip, the Apoſtles language is a confirmation of their belief in that Chriſt Jeſus, who believe in God, thy language is to deſtroy their belief in that Chriſt Jeſus, who beleeve in God, and ſo thou art manifeſted to deny both the Father and the Son, 2 <hi>John</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>Thou bids me peruſe thy paper again, and ſee if thou ſaidſt not, no other Jeſus do I own but the Lamb of God, which was ſlain from the beginning of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thy expreſſions in that, is but the liberty thou takes for oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and to deceive thereby thoſe who hear thee; for the name of Chriſt or Lamb ſlain, or Redeemer, or Annointed, thou doſt but uſe them words, to exalt thy pretended light within, that ſo thou mayſt bring down and deny that Chriſt whom thy fellows ſlew at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and this all may ſee, who have but half an eye of diſcerning, to be the whole drift of thee, &amp; the reſt with thee; hadſt thou ſaid no other Jeſus do I own but the man Chriſt, who dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and faith in him only to be Salvation, thou hadſt ſome cauſe to bid me peruſe thy paper, but whoever peruſeth thy paper or thee, ſhal not find that, and that not being in thee, all thy expreſſions of Chriſt, and light, or unction, or womans ſeed, and the like, are falſely applyed to thy ſecret invention.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaiſt, I tell thee in two ſeveral places, that thou crucifies Chriſt again; and that I break forth into rage, becauſe thou tells me he is ſlain in me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I told thee thou would crucifie the Son of God again, and good cauſe had I, when thou told me, not only that he is ſlain in me as thou here ſaiſt, but alſo that he is ſtill ſlain for me which here thou ſaiſt not; which is the continuance of thy deceit, to leave out that which thou knows will moſt diſcover thy falſhood: is not this plain lying, and diſſembling in thee? to tell the world I ſaid that, which I ſaid not, and to cry out againſt me, and diſſemble the cauſe; But thou art aſhamed truly to declare to the world what I ſaid to thee, and the occaſion, becauſe thou knew it would confound thee: that which
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119118:15"/>thou calls my raging, was my alledging the Scriptures againſt thy falſe affirming Chriſt to be ſtill ſlain for me: which Scriptures prove that Chriſt the Lamb that was ſlain is alive for evermore, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. and that he once ſufferered for ſins, the juſt for the unjuſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. and that he was once offered to take away the ſin of man, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.25, 26, 28.</p>
            <p>But thou (ſaid I) dares ſay is ſtill ſlain for me; was his firſt death inſufficient, and ſhall Chriſt from his immortal and glorifyed being be brought down to die, and ſuffer again; let the Reader now judge what breaking forth into rage is in this? he who affirms Chriſt Jeſus to be ſtill ſlain for ſinners, muſt deny him to be riſen from the grave, &amp; aſcended, make right application of this, or let the wiſe of the nation that hears thee, do it: if Chriſt be ſtill ſlain for me (as thou ſaiſt he is) it muſt be bodily, for ſo was his dying for ſinners, then is he in the grave, and not riſen or aſcended, but thou ſaiſt, the heaven which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains Chriſt, is a myſtery to my dark mind: But I anſwer, 'tis rather thy dark mind which to ſet up thy myſtery of iniquity, would cloud the Heaven that contains Chriſt according to the Scriptures, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21. and 1, 11.</p>
            <p>Thou returns a ſlender account of my counſel given unto thee, to leave thy falſe luminaries, and turn thy feet into the teſtimonies of the true light, in calling me lyer, and falſe Prophet, blaſphemer, and ſuch like: but thoſe who were but in doubt before, will now be fully ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, what light is in thee, compared with the pure peaceable Spirit, and mind of wiſedome, <hi>John</hi> 9.8. the Leopard ſaiſt thou cannot change his ſpots, and 'tis hard for thee to leave thy lying; thou ſaiſt, I kill the Scriptures, can that which is dead be killed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I did not ſay thou killed the Scriptures, doſt not thou tell a lye then to ſay I ſaid ſo; I ſaid thou would kill the Scriptures (if thou could) when thou ſhould obey them, and have them alive again to defend thee againſt others, and this was becauſe ſometimes thou ſaid, the Scriptures thou owned, and that they were yours, and that thou owned that which gave forth the leaves, and would bring them forth to condemn others: and at other times when thou art called upon to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey them, thou calls them dead letter, and life-leſs books, and ſaiſt, it is a damnable doctrine to ſay the Spirit is received by the hearing of faith preached, and believing according to the Apoſtles preaching in the Scriptures; let the reader now judge whether this loud out-cry againſt me of lying, be not juſtly returned upon the head of the cryer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Martin,</hi> I have told thee, and many of thy generation, that you
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119118:16"/>cannot kill the Scriptures, but that they are and will be a continual liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt you, and all oppoſers of truth, and though thou ſay, can that which is dead be killed, yet doſt thou and thy fellows make all the vile warr you can againſt them, in which you find them ſo living that it is a torment unto you, and makes you rage againſt the remnant of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-ſeed who keep the commandements of God, and faith of Jeſus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Thou asks, if in two ſeveral places, I do not call the Scripture, dead letter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If I do, 'tis where I call thee a Saint; ſee if thou canſt find that in my paper: thou tells me I run on in lying, becauſe I ſaid thou runs for ſhelter amonſt thoſe thou accounts thy enemies, who knows no other burial with Chriſt, but burial in water, calling them the cheif Princes of <hi>Meſhech</hi> and <hi>Tubal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Had not I good cauſe to tell thee of running for ſhelter to thy enemies, when thou runs to defend thy ſelf againſt Baptiſme with the word ſprinkling, a word begun and uſed in way of contempt, by thoſe whom thou and thy generation are againſt, as much as againſt me; yet art forced to make uſe of their weak weapons having none of thy own in this caſe: and now to make them more of thy ſide, and to riſe with thee againſt me, thou ſaiſt I call them the cheif Princes of <hi>Meſhech</hi> and <hi>Tubal,</hi> but let my paper be looked on with impartial eyes, and it will be told thee, 'tis applyed to thee, and thy generation, and all who are found to band themſelves againſt the Baptiſme of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, I not nominating any particular but him I writ to, though thou ſay, I mean thoſe called dippers, yet thou haſt not the word dipper from me.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaiſt I have invented an abominable lye, beſides non-ſence in two lines, and this abominable lye and non-ſence, is becauſe I ſay, thou bids me prove whether Chriſt commanded Baptiſme to his Diſciples yea or nay, and did the Lord require it of his people to this day, yea or nay.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Was not the matter we had in queſtion Baptiſme, ſee my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>James Naylors</hi> ſixt poſition ſet down in thy former paper, my words there are theſe; it is not faith but a fancy, to run to other helps, then the Spirit received by the hearing of faith preached by Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, all other teaching or Spirits are but lying vanities, leading to the denyal of obedience in that faith required, as in the Baptiſme of repentance, and the like; thou undertaking to reply to this, ſaid, 'tis indeed thy darling, thy <hi>Diana</hi> which muſt down: is thy ſprinkling with water the Baptiſme of Chriſt, did the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119118:16"/>or require it of his people to this day? Now the reader (thy cloak being taken off) may ſee the abominable lie &amp; non-ſence: whether in me, who anſwers thee according to the matter in queſtion, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not rather in thy ſelf, who to flie the anſwer, talkeſt of ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, which is from the matter, and is neither darling, or <hi>Diana</hi> of mine, but that thou muſt dandle ſuch babbles to delude the ſpectators: ſurely thou art not ſo blind in thy ſelf as thou ſeems to be, to think that any who can hear right from wrong, will not hear thy guiltineſs of Lying and non-ſence: to call upon me to prove Sprinkling which belongs not to our queſtion, to avoid thy anſwer in denyal of Baptiſme. But though thou canſt not ſay any thing in anſwer, thou can tell how to give the lie; its an obſervable thing in thee, that when thou haſt the leaſt to anſwer, thou makeſt the greateſt noyſe in railing accuſations, thinking thereby to take off the Reader from ſeeing thy folly: but the wiſe will ſoon deſcern thy poverty, and miſerable nakedneſs.</p>
            <p>Thou thinks it not enough to tell me, I vent an abominable lie &amp; non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, (for ſpeaking truth) but fearing that inſufficient to effect thy will, thou telleſt me, thou never knew of one pretending to more piety then I, that excelled, or equalled me in the devilliſh art of lying.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Surely the violence of thy evil diſeaſe, through deluſion will appear to all men; I cannot but think thou ſpeakeſt contrary to what thy thoughts are of me; what a miſerable condition is thine, in this to accuſe me, not only to them who knows me not, but alſo to them who knows me, of that which in thy thoughts thou doſt not think is ſo; but thy denyal of truth in me, is to cover thy denyal of truth in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as in the matter in queſtion, the Baptiſme of repentance, which yet remains a Conquering truth, over all thy Sprinklings, and Lyes, and non-ſence, which paper-walls thou patches together, to defend thee from anſwering what was charged upon thee in the point of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaiſt, in the art of Lying, I am a noble ſervant to my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That doth but ſhew the pride of thy fathers child, who would have a ſervant under him.</p>
            <p>In which pride, thou ſaiſt for the ſimples ſake, thou wilt peruſe thoſe Scriptures my father ſends me with, to fight for his kindgome, which Scripture is, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.32, 41, 42.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Let the Reader take notice, that theſe being the Scriptures of God and weapons given by him to thoſe he ſends, for their defence and ſafety againſt the enemy, thou muſt either acknowledge God to be my
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119118:17"/>Father, (agianſt thy will) in bringing theſe Scriptures; or ſay they are not his, but the Scriptures, and weapons of his enemy: which Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy being lodged in thy calling it dead Letter, will be laid open, that all may ſee whoſe Child thou art. But howſoever this is certain that it is not God, whoſe the Scriptures is, that ſends thee with theſe low wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of ſelf devices to fight againſt the ſender of thoſe Scriptures, and thoſe ſent of him; but all thy labour will be in vain, and deſtruction will be the wages of ſuch Imployment; thy promiſe to the ſimple is ſpoken in thy mother tongue, <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.16. They muſt be ſimple ones in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that gives ear to thy Doctrine, and peruſal of Scripture. Thy firſt peruſal is, thou telleſt the ſimple thou cannot find Sprinkling there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is a ſimple inſtruction, he muſt needs be a blind guide, that can but tell thoſe he undertakes to teach, that he cannot ſee, or can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find, and ſo produce nothing; thou canſt not find Sprinkling, and thou wilt not find Baptiſme there, though the Scriptures plainly declare it; the ſimple will ſoon have enough of thy peruſal of Scripture; from whence thou runneſt ſtumbling to me in thy blindneſs, and asks, if <hi>Act.</hi> the 22.16. make for my purpoſe, and if Sprinkling with water is once mentioned there, or did <hi>Annanias</hi> bid him be Baptiſed with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward water.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That Scripture is for me in the matter in queſtion, which is Baptiſme, <hi>Annanias</hi> bid him ariſe and be Baptiſed, and he aroſe and was Baptiſed, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.18. as for thy words Sprinkling with water, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward water, being no Scripture Language but thy own, having thy tongue dipt in the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Sea, and but trifles, and babbles of thine to ſhift off the anſwer; I ſhall leave them, ſee if thou can produce any thing from thence, that will anſwer thy rejecting that counſel of God, againſt thy ſelf in not being Baptiſed, as thy brother Expounders and peruſers of Scriptures did, <hi>Luke</hi> the 7.30.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaiſt, as for <hi>Act.</hi> the 10.47, 48. is it not clear, the Holy Ghoſt was received without outward water, then where is the neceſſity of Sprinkling?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No neceſſity of Sprinkling, but where <hi>Martin Maſon</hi> wants an anſwer, In his denyal of Saptiſme with water upon confeſſion of faith; and for the neceſſity of that Baptiſme, the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> in that Text gives full ſatisfaction, both in asking who could forbid water, and alſo in commanding them to be Baptized; it appears none of thy Spirit was there, for then there would have been a denyal of it: but there was no denyal or forbidding, but ſubmiſtion, and command for it, both in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119118:17"/>
               <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt, and for the Holy Ghoſt being received before that Baptiſme, that is nothing to thy denyal thereof, for none in denyal of Baptiſme, either then or ſince, did receive or have the promiſe of the ſpirit; Gods love to theſe in the State of ſubmiſſion, &amp; obedience to that Ordinance, as <hi>Cornclius</hi> and the reſt were, is no preſident for thee or any in oppoſing, and denying it: but to condemne your diſobedience, <hi>Cornclius</hi> did manifeſt as much, and more light then thee and thy gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration do now, before <hi>Peter</hi> was ſent unto him, yet had he not the ſpirit of promiſe, till he had heard the Apoſtles preaching the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, in whom he believed, and after that there was no ſlighting water, but it was adminiſtred in the name of the Lord Jeſus; In which Name, any thing commanded and practiſed by the Apoſtles, and beleevers was accounted neceſſary, and ſtill is, but where the Spirit of errour doth Blaſpheme, and deny the Lord in his Ordinances. Did Chriſt himſelf, give an example of righteouſueſs in being Baptized with water, upon which the Holy Ghoſt did witneſs the good pleaſure and love of God, and ſhall men now be heard or accounted as righteous, in oppoſition, and denyal thereof, ſurely none will give eare to ſuch ſtrangers, and enemies to truth, but ſuch as know not the Lord, and have no acquaintance with his voyce.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaiſt <hi>Act.</hi> 8.36, 37. intimates, that it is but a thing indifferent, if thou beleeveſt, ſaith <hi>Philip,</hi> thou maiſt; as much as if he had ſaid, if thou beleeveſt outward water to be neceſſary to Salvation, thou maiſt be Baptized.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Take away (as much as) thy prologue to proceed falſely) &amp; the remainder is, if <hi>Philip</hi> had ſaid, if thou believeſt outward water to be neceſſary to Salvation, thou maiſt be Baptized: but <hi>Philip</hi> ſaid not ſo, 'tis <hi>Martin Maſon</hi> that ſaith ſo, in which he hath manifeſted himſelf in a Lye, as much as if he had ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, <hi>Philip</hi> taught the <hi>Eunuch</hi> not to believe in Chriſt; for if <hi>Philip</hi> had taught the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> that to believe outward water, was neceſſary to Salvation, to fit him for Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, he muſt deny belief in Chriſt, which only is neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to fit for Baptiſme, for there is nothing can fit for Baptiſme, but only faith in Chriſt: water adminiſtred upon that faith is neceſſary to obedience, which the <hi>Eunuch</hi> obſerved from <hi>Philips</hi> preaching, deſiring water, but <hi>Philips</hi> preaching, and the <hi>Eunuch</hi> beleeving, was in that Chriſt only as <hi>verſ.</hi> 35. doth manifeſt, according to Chriſts command, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15, 16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. Of whom ſhould the <hi>Eunuch</hi> know, and why ſhould he deſire Baptiſme, if <hi>Philip</hi> had not preached it to him; and for thee to ſay that <hi>Philip</hi> who
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119118:18"/>preached, and was ſent by the power of the Holy Ghoſt, preached things in relation to the Goſpel, ſo indifferently as thou ſaiſt, as to be done, or. not done, thou doſt in this diſable, (what thou can) the Spirit of the moſt high God, to ſay he commands, and ſends his ſervants to practiſe things of no value, or that are unneceſſary, and things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different to be done or undone, which is blaſphemy; or ſay that <hi>Philip</hi> and the Apoſtles did contrary to commandment, or the Spirit teaching, and ſo make them Antichriſtians like to thy ſelf.</p>
            <p>This indifferent Spirit of thine, which would take men off from the commands of Chriſt, &amp; practice of his Diſciples, is a Spirit of errour and Doctrine of Darkneſs, and none but thoſe who are led by ſuch en evil Spirit, would or durſt ſo groſly oppoſe the plain teaching of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and bring their own lye againſt it. The next proof thou faiſt I clap in, is no better then the reſt, which is, <hi>Acts</hi> the 8.12. They were all baptized both men and women, but water was wanting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is no want of water where the baptiſme of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is truly miniſtred, as there it was, and the Baptiſme of the Holy Ghoſt they had not till afterward, as <hi>verſe</hi> 15, 16, 17. But thou wanteſt a Chriſtian eye, and heart, which if thou hadſt thou wouldſt hate to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver ſuch deteſtable Stuff, where the Scripture names water in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, thou with wicked violence wouldſt pluck the words away, and place thy own diviſed baubles in the room thereof, and where the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaks of the ſame baptiſme, becauſe it names not water, thou au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datiouſly denyeſt water, &amp; ſaiſt it's wanting there, by which thy Spirit of lying is plainly laid open: thou calls me vain Jangler, &amp; tells me theſe places are not for my purpoſe without adding to the letter; but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou in thy peruſal or rather abuſal of Scripture, haſt not mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted thy ſelf a vain Jangler, and adds to and diminiſheth of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, teaching to hide and deny the truth, let the reader Judge; thou ſaiſt <hi>John</hi> was a Propher, therefore his Miniſtration muſt end in Chriſt Jeſus, who is the fullfiling of the Law and the Prophets.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What's all that to thy denyal of the Baptiſme of repentance, or baptizing with water upon confeſſion of faith, and ſins. If <hi>John</hi> were a Prophet he was ſo in relation to the Goſpel of Chriſt, whoſe ſervant and Miniſter he was; and not in relation to the ceremonies, and rudimeuts of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> therefore his miniſtration ending in Chriſt, ending but where it began as all other Prophets miniſtration of the Goſpel did, as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> whoſe miniſtration begun and ended in Chriſt, but all in relation to their own perſons, for that miniſtration ſtill remained, and doth remain: to ſay the miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119118:18"/>of Baptiſme ceaſed when <hi>John</hi> ceaſed, is not only a tying the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and commandements of God to mans mutability, but is alſo a plain denyal of the Apoſtles teaching, and practice to be of God, not only after <hi>John</hi> was taken away, but alſo after Chriſt himſelf aſcended, as <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. and 10.47, 48. and 6.38.</p>
            <p>Thou askeſt me why I do not plead for the practice of circumciſion in the fleſh, as for Baptiſme, is not their authority of an equal purity, both by permiſſion, not by precept.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If I ſhould plead for the practice of circumciſion in the fleſh now, as for baptiſme, I ſhould be a denyer of Chriſt like unto thee, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion being a carnal ſeal of a worldly covenant was aboliſhed by the bringing in of a better teſtament, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.22. and the 10.9. But I plead for Baptiſme becauſe 'tis an ordinance of the Goſpel, and a Teſtimonial of their faith, and obedience, who enter into the new cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: thy ſaying they are of equal purity, is from an impure weakneſs, for the one was only an impreſſion in the fleſh, not reaching the heart by faith; the other hath no Seal or impreſſion, but in the heart, by faith; &amp; whereas thou ſaiſt, they were both by permiſſion, not by precept: thou ſpeakeſt falſly; for they were both by precept, the one a precept of the law; the other a precept of Chriſt in the Goſpel, which all that obey the light that lights every man, that comes into the World, knowes and will acknowledg, but thoſe on whom the ſun is gone down, night is to them for a viſion, and darkneſs for a divination. Thou ſaiſt in my reply to the ſeventh Poſition, thou findeſt me ſo puzled teaching perfection; that I give thee no anſwer, but would ſhuffle thee off, bringing in, <hi>James</hi> the 3.2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou doſt this but to ſhuffle off <hi>James</hi> 3.2. To which thou ſhould give anſwer, whoſoever reads thy former paper, ſhall hear thee throw me out a many foul and filthy words, about perfection, which is all that is contained in that paper to puzle me with, which pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per if thou wert not aſhamed to ſhow to the world with my anſwer, it would manifeſt who is puzled, and what perfection there is in <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Maſon,</hi> compared with what thou repeats from, <hi>James</hi> 3.2. If any offend not in word, the ſame is a perfect man; if thy own mouth do not here condem thee, let thy offenſive words (which teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thy deceived and vain Religion, <hi>James</hi> 1.26.) witneſs, which is becauſe thou wants a bridle which will bring thee a ſad concluſion as <hi>James</hi> tells thee, <hi>James</hi> 3.3. to the 7. But now let the reader hear what anſwer there is in thee, to that of <hi>James</hi> 3.2. which thou ſaiſt I ſhuffle thee off with, the Apoſtle, there ſaith to his brethren, in many things we ſin all: In the room of an anſwer, ſaiſt thou, doth he plead
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119118:19"/>againſt perfection as thou doſt? to which I anſwer, Thou muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg he doth, or ſay he calls ſin perfection, ſee if thou can ſhuffle this off.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaiſt, the Scriptures were never writ that the Devil by them ſhould plead for ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Nor were they ever writ that ſinners by them ſhould plead perfection? Thou telleſt me of bringing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18. Where <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>I know that in me, that is in my fleſh, dwells no good thing;</hi> from whence (ſaiſt thou) thou would infer, that in <hi>Paul</hi> dwelt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that was good; but wilt thou ſay the Holy Ghoſt is not good?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I brought <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18. to let thee hear the Apoſtles own words, which denyeth perfection in the fleſh, thou canſt not tell how to anſwer this, and therefore leaves it, to ſpeak faſly of me, ſaying, I would infer; had I brought the Second commandement to a Papiſt againſt his worſhiping of Images, and he anſwer, hence thou would infer, that God ſhould not be worſhiped, it had been an anſwer equal with thine.</p>
            <p>Thou ought rather to anſwer that Scripture, or acknowledg thy er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, <hi>Paul</hi> had the holy Ghoſt, yet <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, in him, that is, in his fleſh dwelleth no good thing; but thou ſaiſt perfection, dwelleth in the fleſh of <hi>Paul,</hi> ſo that the perfection thou pleads for is no good thing, or we muſt deny <hi>Paul,</hi> and hear thee againſt him; but if <hi>Paul</hi> who had the Spirit of God within him, had no good thing dwelling in his fleſh, as himſelf ſaith, then ſure 'tis a bad perfection that is in <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Maſons</hi> floſh, in whom dwelleth the Spirit of errour, as is manifeſt in his abuſe of Scripture, and fighting againſt the truth.</p>
            <p>And then ſaiſt thou, away with <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles, and by conſequence with the reſt of the Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is it thou ſtrives for, to get ſhut of the Scriptures, for their witneſs torments thee, but thou labours in vain, for they will out-live all the generations of falſhood, and be a continual witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mens devices, as is plainly manifeſted in this.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaiſt that I alledged, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.24. is to me a myſtery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I have ſo much of the myſtery as to alledg it for that which thou art not able to anſwer, therefore in that I need not ſay to them, babler be ſilent; thou ſaiſt my piece of Logick ſhews what a Pagan I am.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> And thy ſilence argues thy conſent, to the right reaſon in that piece of Logick, for thou giveſt no anſwer to it, whether it be more Pagan-like to frame right reaſon, or deny it without reaſon, let thy friends judge.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:119118:19"/>
            <p>Thou biddeſt me conſider in the cool of the day, that which is born of the fleſh is fleſh; but that which is born of the Spirit is Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In the cool of the day I do conſider, and in that coolneſs tell thee, that this is ſufficient to diſcover, that notwithſtanding all thy hot words againſt me about perfection, in the mind through faith, but not perfection in the fleſh; till Mortal have put on Immortality, that outward man is born of the fleſh, and is fleſh; therefore not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; the inward man or mind (in the ſtate of faith) is born of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and therefore perfect; in which perfection of the mind, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith he ſerves the Law of God, but in his imperfect fleſh the Law of ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.25. All thy following words about perfection, at the end of which thou writes the word <hi>Queries,</hi> is a repetition, not prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing for thee, for the Tabernacle of God with men, and dwelling in them, and walking in them, and the like, is all included in that afore alledged of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> his having the holy Ghoſt in him, yet the ſame Apoſtle ſaith, that in his fleſh dwells no good thing; this thou ſhouldſt anſwer too, and prove perfection in that which <hi>Panl</hi> denyeth, or acknowledg thy error, or ſpeak plainly that all may hear thee, as one of thy generation did to me; alledging that Scripture to him, who adorning his ſpeech with thy manner of language, of beaſt and lyer, and filthie creature, and ſuch like; Said, <hi>Paul</hi> was no Chriſtian when he wrote that; thou askeſt me, why I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that to be the true Spirit, or true unction which is not received by the letter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That Spirit, which denyeth the Apoſtles teaching in the Scriptures, and is not received by the hearing, and believing their preaching of faith, I deny, becauſe 'tis a lying Spirit, and cometh but to deceive.</p>
            <p>Had not, (ſaiſt thou) <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and the reſt of the holy men of God, who lived before <hi>Moſes</hi> writ the Letter, had not they the Spirit of truth within them? were there not many deceitful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents and filthy Spirits like thine, in their dayes, and had they any outward writing given them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What though <hi>Abrabam,</hi> and the reſt thou ſpeakeſt of, in their time had the Spirit of truth within them before the Law written by <hi>Moſes?</hi> doth that give cauſe to any in time of the Law, to deny the writing by <hi>Moſes,</hi> or thee, or any now to deny the writings of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, if there were ſuch Serpents, and filthy Spirits, as thou ſpeakeſt of, who oppoſed the cammand of God, yet that doth not excuſe the deceitful Serpents, and filthy Spirits, that now deny
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119118:20"/>the written verities, as thou and thy generation do: that Spirit which led men to obey the commandements of God or Law of faith, before <hi>Moſes</hi> writ the Law, which if it were not by writing, yet it was by voyce, which is all one, for that which was given to <hi>Abraham</hi> by voyce was written for our learning, and what was given to the Apoſtles by voyce, was alſo written for our learning, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. That we through patience and comfort of the Scriptures, might have hope, that Spirit I ſay that led men before the Law written, to obey, did alſo lead men to obey the Law written by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and whoſoever denyed, and deſpiſed that Law was led by an evil Spirit, and it was death without mercy, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.28. Even ſo now that Spirit that led men before the Law, and in the Law, to obey the commandements of God by faith, the ſame Spirit now doth lead men to obey all the commandements, and teachings of Chriſt Jeſus in the Law of the Goſpel preached, and written by the Apoſtles, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.37. But whoſoever denyeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and would trample that down, as thou and thy fellows, they are led by an evil Spirit, and their ſorer puniſhment is told them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. did <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles, (ſaiſt thou) receive the Spirit of truth by vertue of reading, or hearing any writing or book without them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> All the Apoſtles did firſt hear the voice of Chriſt, who was their Book or Writing without them, before they received the Spirit of Truth within them: Produce if thou canſt any of the Apoſtles who had the Spirit of Promiſe within them, before Chriſt had firſt called them with his voyce without them.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaiſt, That which thou broughteſt out of 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. as to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing ſtands unſhaken, and cannot be removed by all the Brats of <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That which thou broughteſt, is not like to be ſhaken by the brats of <hi>Babylon,</hi> (except againſt their wills) as the fooliſh woman de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes her own houſe) for 'tis their own bringing, but if that, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. and all other declarations of the holy Ghoſt, in the Scriptures, could be ſhaken, they had been ere now, for thou and thy generation lay all your bones and ſinews to ſhake it, but it is grounded on a Rock, and hath its being and protection from the Lord of Power, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is it that (like your predeceſſors) you are ſo marvelouſly beaten back in your aſſaults againſt it: what haſt thou to do with the annoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpoken of, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. it doth not belong, nor is it in the denyers of Chriſt, 'tis onely the Saints Seal and Aſſurance of the love and favour of God to them, which thoſe know not who are in the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119118:20"/>ſtate of diſobedience againſt the Law of Faith, for without Faith no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe or ſealing in the New Covenant: And no Faith where no Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to that Teaching is denied: Thou publiſheſt this to the World, to make them think thou hadſt ſaid ſomething, but it is a plain teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (to all that hear thy former Paper with my Anſwer) of thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, here not being a word in anſwer to any thing ſaid to thee, but Repetitions weakly, as well as in thy amazement thou couldſt. Thou talkeſt of the Pope, but thou canſt not free thy ſelf, with all the skill and ſtrength thou haſt, of the compariſon I made betwixt you; You both boaſt of Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, and both deny that Chriſt who came in his own fleſh, for you both deny his teachings and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands given while he was here in the fleſh, and ſet up your own inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt him, and therefore are alike Antichriſtian, and ſo as is Propheſied of you in <hi>Daniel,</hi> though you ſeem to war and contend one againſt another, yet you talk of deceit at one Table, talking of Chriſt come in the fleſh, by which he cals himſelf Chriſts Vicar, (or Chriſt on Earth) and thou and thy generation, ſo many as there are of you, would be ſo many Chriſts, like another of your Predeceſſours, <hi>Henry Nicolas,</hi> the Father of the Familiſts, whoſe breath ſome years agon hath blown theſe ſwarms, that thus darken the Sun, and infect the Air; He denied Salvation by Chriſt who died at Jeruſalem, as you do, and ſaid, That the ſtate of Perfection is the Man Chriſt, or any power in man whereby he can keep the Law, without Faith in the Man Chriſt. Is not this the Doctrine taught by thee and thy generation, all which is to ſet up your ſelves to be the coming of Chriſt in the fleſh, denying that Chriſt that came in the fleſh, which the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> teacheth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.1, 2. thy expoſition of which, to pervert the Truth, doth manifeſt no leſſe; which is, that the Apoſtle meanes, Chriſt come in the fleſh of others; though all the Apoſtles in their preaching doth preach belief in that one Chriſt that came in his own fleſh, or perſon, in which he ſuffered at Jeruſalem for the ſins of all men, and not in the fleſh of others, as thou expoundeſt; for that is the coming of thoſe who ſay, <hi>loe here and loe there,</hi> which are falſe Chriſts, forewarned of, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. Who to ſet up themſelves and throw down Chriſt Jeſus, by falſe Expoſitions pervert the Scriptures; by which is manifeſt who rules in the fleſhly tabernacles of ſuch Children of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p>It is but the Lyer (ſaiſt thou) that tels me, my Maſter hath not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded me to judge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. Martin,</hi> thou wilt not ſeem to take notice, becauſe the world
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119118:21"/>ſhould not know, that I told thee, there is difference betwixt a Judge and a Malefactor; I told thee, thou ſhouldeſt anſwer thy own Maker at the Bar, and ſtay taking upon thee the Judges place till thou be a Saint, and then thou wilt know that thy Maſter (whom thou now cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt the Singlo Perſon) that died at Jeruſalem, and is alive for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, bids thee judge not, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.37. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. to bear off this blow, thou bringeſt Chriſts words, <hi>John</hi> 12.48. <hi>He that rejecteth me, and receiveth not my word, hath one that judgeth him;</hi> but this is no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence for thee, but wounds thee deeper, for Chriſt tels thee there what one that is that ſhall judge, which is, <hi>the Word</hi> that he hath ſpoken; which thou calleſt, <hi>the dead Letter:</hi> But thou, to deceive by, thoughtſt to keep this out, that thou mighteſt take the Judges place thy ſelf, and ſo to exalt thy ſelf above Chriſt, and then ſayſt, he is thy witneſſe. O bold preſumption, was ever a greater exaltation in a cative ſo low!</p>
            <p>Chriſt came not (ſaiſt thou) to ſend peace but the ſword, to the Man of ſin whom thou ſerveſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> And yet I am farre from ſerving thee or any ſuch exalters of themſelves againſt Chriſt; if thou underſtoodeſt thoſe words of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.34, 35, 36. part of which thou haſt ſtolen to ſpeak proudly with, thou wouldſt not have placed them thus, but wouldſt have known that they are nothing for thy purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Thou talkeſt of the Saints Judging the World, and the Spirituall man judging all things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As I have told thee, Stay till thou be a Saint, and then thou wilt not be ſo haſty to be a Judge, but wilt better know how and when ſuch Judgement ſhall be; and that the Spirituall mans judging, is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning all things, not judging or cenſuring perſons, and then thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of Faith and obedience to Chriſt and his Goſpel, will be a judging and reproof to unfaithfulneſſe, and thy tongue will be taught more tameneſſe, then to ſmite others therewith, for then the Spirit of God will tell thee, that thou haſt nothing to do to judge another mans Servant, he ſtands or fals to his own Maſter, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.4. then thou wilt learn to ſpeak with a new tongue, and that old blaſphemous curſing preſumptuous tongue, that runs without guide, will be plucke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out, and be no more the loud belman to a corrupt heart.</p>
            <p>Thou askeſt me, By what authority. I judge thee for an enemy of righteouſneſſe, and why I judge the People called Dippers, calling them the chief Princes of <hi>Meſhech</hi> and <hi>Tubal,</hi> and by what authority I judge the Prieſts of the Nation for Antichriſtians?</p>
            <p>I judge thee not, I leave that to him to whom thy judgement and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119118:21"/>condemnation doth belong, the Word of God tells thee, of thy enmity againſt righteouſneſſe, in warring againſt that Word. Where have I judged the people thou calleſt Dippers, or called them the chief Princes of <hi>Meſhech</hi> and <hi>Tubal,</hi> ſhew it if thou canſt? Or where I have named the Dippers in my Paper upon any ſuch account: It is with thee, as I told thee formerly, thou wouldeſt ſhelter thy ſelf amongſt others, thou ſeeſt thy want, and wouldſt have help in the defence of thy cauſe; which maketh thee cry alſo to the Prieſts of the Nation (as thou calleſt them) telling them I judge them Antichriſtians; Thou art driven to a great ſtraight ſurely, thou takeſt me for ſome forraine enemy, that wilt thus claw thy domeſtick enemies, to engage with thee againſt me, but thou doſt trouble thy neighbours with ſuch a falſe alarm; when I have occaſion with, either thoſe thou calleſt Prieſts or Dippers, I ſhall ſtand up in the manifeſtation of truth according to what I have received from the Lord, and ſhal leave the judging or cenſuring them and all men to him to whom all judgement doth belong, and my ſelf, ſhall not judge or paſſe ſentence on any man.</p>
            <p>Thou telleſt me, I ſhame not in one of my Arguments to affirm, that the Letter, under the Name of the words of Chriſt, is Spirit and Life in it ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What cauſe have I to be aſhamed of affirming the very word of Chriſt himſelf, <hi>John</hi> 6.36. but thou haſt cauſe to be aſhamed of thy ly, ſaying, I affirm the Letter, which is a word of thy own and not of mine.</p>
            <p>In another place (ſaiſt thou) thou concludeſt the Spirit of God in the Apoſtles, who were Saints, is the Rule to try and diſcern falſe Spirits.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> If I do, tis no contradiction of the former, ſeeing the word of Chriſt and Spirit of God in the Apoſtles were one, and ſpake one and the ſame thing. The truth is <hi>Martin,</hi> thou wouldeſt gladly ſay ſomething to my Argument, but thou canſt not, thou knoweſt that way of arguing was begun by thee, in which if thou hadſt dealt faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with thoſe to whom thou haſt ſo generally divulged our difference, they would plainly ſee where the right of reaſoning is, and who hath moſt cauſe to be aſhamed of their Argument.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaieſt, the Spirit of God in the Apoſtles, at their death return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to God that gave it them, but (ſaiſt thou) wouldſt thou have me as ſottiſh as thy ſelf, to ſay and unſay, and own their Writings to be the Spirit of God: This thou writeſt to deny the Apoſtles preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119118:22"/>and teachings to be the infallible Rule to try the Spirits whether they be of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That Spirit which the Scriptures ſpeakes of from whence thou hadſt that ſaying (the Spirit returns to God that gave it) though thou quote it not, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.7. is not that Spirit by which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did preach Chriſt and work miracles, but of the Spirit which is the mooving and acting in the bodily being of all men, which the Apoſtles had before they received the gift of the Spirit of promiſe, therefore how ſottiſh ſoever I am, this muſt needs be an ignorant blindneſſe in thee, thus to uſe Scripture words againſt Scripture teaching, to pervert them to extinguiſh if thou couldeſt, the ſpeaking of the Spirit of God therein, that thou mayeſt bring them into a dead and dry eſtimation, that ſo thy falſe Spirit might act at Libetty, but the Spirit ſpeaking in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, is of ſuch lively power and authority, that it will quaſh and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume thoſe riſings and out-burnings of the man of ſin; and by that which is written, which thou calleſtdead, &amp; wouldeſt have denied, as now ſhall be made manifeſt to thy confuſion. The Spirit of God ſaith to <hi>John Revel.</hi> 1.11. <hi>That which thou ſeeſt writ in a book, and ſend to the Seaven Churches that are in Aſia:</hi> Compare this with that which followes in that Book written, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Let him that hath an car hear, what the Sprirt ſaith to the Churches;</hi> By which tis plain, (to the daſhing down of thy denyals thereof) that Book writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>John,</hi> is the Spirits ſpeaking to the Churches: Compare this with what our Saviour ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 6.63. <hi>The words that I ſpeak to you are Spirit and life,</hi> So that the Scriptures muſt either be denied to be the words of Chriſt, or owned to be the ſpeaking of the Spirit, but to acknowledge them to be the words of Chriſt Jeſus and deny them to be the ſpeaking of the Spirit, or to be Spirit and life (as Chriſt ſaith they are) and call them dead as thou and thy generation doth, is the moſt rediculous, abſurd oppoſition to Chriſt and his Goſpel, that hath been yet: The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.37. <hi>If any man think him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be a Prophet, or Spirituall, let him acknowledge the things that I writ unto you are the Commandments of God;</hi> Are they the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God and not the Spirits ſpeaking: But thou ſaieſt, thou are not ſo ſottiſh as I, to own this: It ſeems thou hadſt rather (truly) be a foole to be eſteemed wiſe in this world, then be a foole that thou mayeſt be truly wiſe. See whether this be ſottiſhneſſe in thee or no, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18.</p>
            <p>But howſoever, thy wiſdome in diſowning the Scriptures to be the ſpeaking of the Spirit, doth ſhew thee to be neither Prophet or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119118:22"/>therefore the Spirit of God will diſown thee, the wolfe would perſwade the weak, that he will keep them for worrying when the danger is only in himſelf.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaiſt, I charge that for a Lyer, for ſaying I own the Letter to be the rule, but one thing is, ſaiſt thou, I need not go far to fetch my proof thou haſt given it under thy hands, in theſe words, therefore the Scriptures are the ſure and infallible rule to try the Spirits, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be of God or no.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> My charging thee for a Lyer, was for ſaying I own the dead Letter, to be the rule, thou ſhuffies out the word dead, but it ſhuts thee not of the ly but makes it a greater ly, what plainer ly can be told then this, to ſay I owned that which I never named to thee, but to deny therein, the word dead Letter is thy own, not mine. If thou call the Goſpels declaration, the <hi>Turkiſh Alcaron,</hi> and I ſay that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Goſpel is the power of God to Salvation to all that hear and obay it, canſt thou reply and ſay, I own the <hi>Turkiſh Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caron</hi> to be the Decleration of the Goſpel without being alyer? and is it not the ſame to ſay, I own the dead letter to be the rule, becauſe I ſay the decleration of the Goſpel is the rule, thou mayſt ſee if thou be not moreſotiſh then I, it is thou that cals it the dead letter or <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>karon</hi> and not I, &amp; therefore the lye muſt needs lodge with thee. Thou ſaiſt I alſo call the words of Chriſt, or Scripture dead Letter; twice in a following argument of mine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For the truths ſake, and that the Lyer may be looked upon, and ſeen of all, I will not only lay down that argument of mine but the occaſion thereof given by thee, in thy argument thus framed.</p>
            <p>He that denyeth to be tryed by the true touch-ſtone, the infallible rule, 'tis an infallible ſign his Spirit is not of God, he is guided by the Spirit of error.</p>
            <p>But thou <hi>Jonathan Johnſon</hi> denyeſt to be tryed by the living prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of God, the light of Chriſt in the conſcience, the Spirit of truth: and wouldeſt be tryed by the dead Letter, therefore thy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is not of God, thou art guided by the Spirit of error.</p>
            <p>This argument I told thee, cometh bare without any proof, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Jonathan Johnſon:</hi> therefore <hi>Martin Maſon</hi> remaineth a lyer till he prove the aſcertion, in the mean time to diſcover what waslapt up in that argument: I from thy own Major popoſition, framed thee this.</p>
            <p>He that denyeth to be tryed by the true touch-ſtone, the Infallible rule, 'tis an infallible ſign his Spirit is not of God, he's guided by the Spirit of error.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:119118:23"/>
            <p>But thou <hi>Jonathan Johnſon,</hi> denyeſt to be tryed by the principle in <hi>Martin Maſon,</hi> and wouldeſt be tryed by the living principle of God, the light of Chriſt, in the Scriptures, Therefore thy Spirit is not of God, thou art guided by the Spirit of error.</p>
            <p>When I had thus laid open the falſhood of thy argument, and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der againſt me without ground or proof, I who can better tell my own deſires and denyals, then thou canſt, to declare truly the ſame, framed thee this argument.</p>
            <p>He that deſires to be tryed by the true touch-ſtone, the infallible rule, the living principle of God, the light of Chriſt in the Saints conſciences, the ſpirit of truth, and not by the dead Letter, 'tis a ſign his Spirit is of God, he is guided by the Spirit of promiſe.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Jonathan Johnſon,</hi> deſires to be tryed as above ſaid. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis a ſign his Spirit is of God, he is guided by the ſpirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Martin</hi> do I here call the words of Chriſt, or Scripture, dead Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, (or any where elſe) waſh thy eyes, and look better over my paper, then ſpeak rightly, and thou wilt ſay my charge is not taken off, neither hath the lyer remooved his lodging, which every paſſer by will now behold, thy boſome being unbuttened. I have not yet told thee what I call the dead Letter, though thou ſay I cal the Scripture ſo, by which is manifeſted, who is the lyer. But now it puts them out of doubt, and to ſatisfie the hearers I will tell thee; It is the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of <hi>Martin Maſon,</hi> and his fellows, and all ſuch as oppoſe the Scriptures teaching, denying the ordinances, and commands of Chriſt there taught.</p>
            <p>Becauſe I eſteem their books or bulks of writings, no better then an Idol, ſet up like the maſſe or ſervice-book to draw men from the true worſhip and ſervice of God, which is according to the Scripture; therefore, If I ſay, the ſame that thou doſt, (as thou ſaiſt I do) then we ſay both one thing, by thy own acknowledgment; But I ſay the dead Letter is the <hi>Quakers</hi> Books: therefore thou ſaiſt the ſame with me, repent thou of thy error in calling the Scriptures dead Letter.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaiſt thou never readeſt, groſſer contradictions to thy knowledg then hath dropt from the pen of this Painted Pagan: (as thou calleſt me)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I believe, <hi>Martin,</hi> the Painter is miſtaken, and ſpoiles his work for want of color; this ſurrilous way of thine, with all the falſeneſs of thy alegations will diſcover thee to all that read the Papers:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119118:23"/>Loud accuſation, and little proof layes open folly, it is a ſmall matter for a man of thy language to be larg upon charging evil upon others; but very ſcant in making good what you charg. Thou ſaiſt in the next place, that for all my folly and confuſion, I muſt give thee another rotten reed of <hi>Egypt</hi> as it were for a farewel, in an argument, which for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance (thou ſaiſt) is thus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I will leave thy ſubſtance, and bring the whole ſubſtance it ſelf, the argument as it was given to thee, by me.</p>
            <p>They, who by an infallible Spirit, were Maſter Builders, and layers of the foundation of the Saints Religion; and who are heard of all who are of God, and who have the Spirit of truth, and who accounts all accurſed, who preach any other Doctrine then they have already preached, muſt needs be the true touch-ſtone, and infallible tryal of Spirits, whether they be of God or no; and denyal to be tryed by them, is a plain teſtimony of an evil cauſe, and that the Spirit is the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of error, and lyer.</p>
            <p>But the Apoſtles were they, who by an infallible Spirit were Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Builders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As theſe Scriptures teſtifie, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9, 10, 11. 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.6. <hi>John</hi> 8.47. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.4. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13, 14, 15. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9, 10. 2 <hi>John</hi> 7.8, 9, 10. And <hi>Martin Maſon,</hi> denyeth their tryal, and calls it dead Letter.</p>
            <p>Therefore his Spirit is not of God, he is guided by the Spirit of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</p>
            <p>Thou, for want of an anſwer to this, calleſt me forgetful, willful, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Beaſt. Did not he even now (ſaiſt thou) a litle before, in his other argument ſay, that he deſired to be tryed by the light in the Saints con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and not by the dead Letter, and yet taxeth me; O bluſh and be a ſhamed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I am neither Beaſt or Lyer, nor forgetful, of what I have ſaid before, I have laid down the plain truth to thee, which is, that the Apoſtles teachings, or Scriptures, is the true touch-ſtone and tryal of Spirits; I have not in any place called them dead Letter, but have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes told thee, that the light in the Saints conſciences is received from thence, therefore I have no cauſe to bluſh or be aſhamed at the truth; the manifeſtation of which makes thee be wrathful, out of which thou brings the Beaſt, and Lyer, and bluſh, and be aſhamed; there not being a word in thy tongue to anſwer, of which if thou cold be aſhamed, there would be hopes of thy repentance, and good cauſe haſt thou to bluſh and be a ſhamed of this proclaming thy folly for 'tis a low diſgrace to one pretending ſuch high things, to be ſo diſcovered
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119118:24"/>as thou art in ſuch want of anſwer, and in evil words corrupting thy good manners.</p>
            <p>According to the grace of God given to me, (ſaiſt thou) as a wiſe Maſter builder, I have laid the foundation, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. he builded upon the rock; other foundation then that is laid, can no man lay, which is Jeſus Chriſt in all, <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Greek, Barbarian, Scithian,</hi> bond and free, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.11. to this unction within, did <hi>Paul</hi> direct the People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whoſoever rules, and obſerves thee, will ſee thy deſire to ſet up thy ſelf for a wiſe Maſter builder, for which read thy motto, <hi>Pro.</hi> 26.12, 16. Thou joynes ſeveral declerations of the Apoſtle together, to pervet them if thou cold, from his Goſpel order of teaching to thy own corrupt ſence, and foyſts in thy own words amongſt, to make fit a lye, the Apoſtle in neither of theſe places, or any where elſe doth direct the people to the unction within them, till firſt they have heard the preaching of the Apoſtles, in the doctrine of faith and believing, thou telleſt me of a brat of my own begeting, but if this be not of thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geting 'tis the begeting of ſome of thy generation, from whom thou haſt received it to nurſe: do not think to Father ſuch prodigious birth upon the Apoſtles, their begeting men to the faith was by preaching Chriſt Jeſus, who was not in thoſe before to whom they preached, that is your falſe invenſion to oppoſe the truth, the Apoſtle ſaith he laid the foundation, thou ſaiſt it was laid in them before, a flat contradiction to the Apoſtles teaching, and the Scripture thou quotes, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.11. Doth not ſay, Chriſt is in all <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> before they received him by faith, through the Apoſtles preaching; but plainly telleth thee (if thy ears cold hear) <hi>verſe 10.</hi> where Chriſt is in all, which is in all them who have put on the new man, which is renued in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg; after the Image of him who hath created him, by which is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt (according to the whole teaching of the Apoſtles) that Chriſt is in all who are in the faith, but in thoſe in whom faith is not, the Apoſtles have not any where ſaid that Chriſt is there. Therefore thy oppoſition to the Apoſtles, and that Chriſt which they preached is made plain; and that thou, and thy fellows would ſet up your own heart-Imaginations, and falſe deceiveings in the place of Chriſt. And would perſwade men of a Chriſt, in all before or without the preaching of faith by the Apoſtles; that they may deny the Apoſtles preaching: and that Chriſt which they preached, to thoſe who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were without him; <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. And where Chriſt was not named, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.30.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119118:24"/>
            <p>That which lay dead, (ſaiſt thou) did at the hearing of the voyce of the Son of God live.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That which hear thou ſaiſt lay dead, is that which before thou calleſt the Chriſt in all, the royal ſeed; the unction, the Lord of glory crucified in them: ſo that by thy doctrine, the royal ſeed, the unction, the Lord of glory, and Chriſt in all, lay dead till it did at the hearing of the voyce of the Son of God live, what greater confuſed nonſence can be delivered, then to ſay Chriſt, the Son of God lyeth dead, till he hear the voyce of Chriſt the Son of God and live; can ſuch babling be without blaſpemy? thoſe who knew, and in whom Chriſt the hope of glory is, will ſee this thy dead Image, that thou would ſet up to deny the Lord that bought thee.</p>
            <p>After thy complaint, of allmoſt wearineſs, thou follows with ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the poor hears (as thou calleſt them) whom thou ſaiſt are wedded to their water, and counts no Saints who ſubmit not to their ceremonies, thou bideſt them anſwer thee in good earneſt, can their <hi>Diana</hi> ſatisfie a hungry Soul.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which the poor hearts reply, that it were better for thee to ſit down and reſt thy ſelf after thy great labour and hot chace, except thou findeſt thy ſelf ſo tyred, that thou deſireſt the refreſhment of thoſe waters, to which they are wedded, to cool thy heat of bloud, and in good earneſt they anſwer thee, they have not <hi>Epheſian Diana,</hi> which they worſhipped walking by thy light, of ſelf-invention, or any other Idol, that may have written upon it, light of Conſcience, quaking, or baptiſme, but they have that Chriſt the Bread of Life, which the <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> believed in after the preaching of the Apoſtles unto them, they feed not upon hid Bread, nor are they wedded to ſtolen waters, they abhor the ſecret devices, and ſelf-inventions, that oppoſe the open Declarations of Gods mind and will in the Scriptures of Truth: They drink of <hi>Shiloh,</hi> the Fountaine open to the houſe of <hi>David:</hi> They feed on <hi>Manna,</hi> the Bread that came down from Heaven, their ſouls love, and are continually refreſhed therewith. Which <hi>Manna,</hi> thou and thy genaration loathes, and calls it light bread, and prize your Garlick and Onions above it, the art of ſowing and growing of which you learnt in <hi>Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou talkeſt of waſhing the body with outward water, and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of a good Conſcience towards God, and who (ſaiſt thou) can witneſs the anſwer of a good conſcience towards God, that is not guided by the light of God in his Conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> And what anſwer of a good Conſcience canſt thou have that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119118:25"/>is not enlightened by the preaching of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, fighting againſt their Doctrine of Faith, and denying all obedience thereto. Doth not thy own Conſcience, when thou conſidereſt of thy anſwer before Chriſt at the day of Account, condemn thee for oppoſing and denying the Command of Chriſt and Practice for diſcipling all Nations, is not thy iniquity there.</p>
            <p>Thou telleſt them they are not come to yea and nay, in their dealing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou talkeſt like a tyred man in Spirits: Produce if thou can that, in any of them, and they will acknowledge tis againſt the Baptiſm of Repentance, which they plead for, and thou denieſt; But thou not proving that againſt them, where is thy yea and nay in thy dealing, thou muſt needs want the uprightneſſe of yea and nay in thy dealing, thus falſly with us accuſing us without ground or proofe: They deny with formall words of yea and nay, to cover the deceit of wrong dealing within, neither do they put on white breeches without, to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the black breeches of bribery and extortion. Look nearer home let not thy eyes be ſcattered in the corners of the World, yea and nay in the tongue, when wrong and falſhood is in the heart, is not the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of Saints. Thou thy felf art farre from that yea and ney in thy dealing or communication with Chriſts commands <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.37 dealing ſuch foul and filthy words to thoſe againſt whom thou ſpeakeſt or writeſt.</p>
            <p>Thou telleſt them of reſpect of perſons and vain cuſtomes and faſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Heathen, and art not yet brought to the bridling of the tongue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe words are thy own, and better applyed to thee, then from thee, the Cuſtomes, and Faſhions of the Heathen, are ſelf-divices againſt the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and Saviour of all men; they own no ſuch ſoul faſhions, or evil Cuſtomes, but deny them and therein deny thee, and thy generation, and your Groves, and Alters, and Calves at <hi>Dan,</hi> and <hi>Bethel.</hi> And for an unbridled Tongue running at ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, cannot be more manifeſted, then in what is breathed from thee; in which all that hear thee with right underſtanding, will ſay tis not the Language of <hi>Sion,</hi> or new tongue ſpeaking of a Saint, but the Language of <hi>Babel,</hi> and ſpeaking like the Draggon.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaiſt, <hi>Paul</hi> told the people he had not ſhuned to declare unto them all the Counſel God: but where did he mention water Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme as a branch thereof, if it had been of the Counſel of God, certainly <hi>Paul</hi> durſt not have concealed it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whoſe Counſel was that which <hi>Peter</hi> gave, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. wilt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119118:25"/>thou denyeſt that to be the Counſel of God, it being the Counſel of God. <hi>Paul</hi> did declare it according to thy own Confeſſion: And whoſe Counſel was it for <hi>Paul</hi> to Baptize <hi>Criſpus,</hi> and <hi>Gaius,</hi> and others; and into whoſe name did he Baptize them, into his own name, or into the name of Chriſt; if into the name of Chriſt, as openly thou dareſt not deny, and not into his own name as himſelf teſtiſyeth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.13, 14. 15. Then muſt it needs be the Counſel of God, which doth condemne, and confound thy abominable denyal thereof: may not the queſtion be rightly put to thee, that our Saviour put to the Scribes, and Prieſts, <hi>Mark.</hi> 11.20. Concerning that Baptiſme, whether it were from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or of man, will it not dazle thee as it did them; thou not only denying that Counſel of God againſt thy ſelf, as they did, <hi>Luke.</hi> 7.30. But alſo denying it to be the Counſel of God, which is a degree of evil exceeding theirs, in that report of them: But if thou ſay thou doſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs it from Heaven; (which thy predeceſſors oppoſers of truth durſt not deny) doſt thou not then condemn thy ſelf in denying it to be the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of God: and thy ſaying, tis of men makes <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor, in doing mans divices in Divine ſervice, and Chriſt a conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with him in it; and ſo the Apoſtles teaching, and practiſe in that Baptiſme, to be all tranſgreſſion and vanity; hadſt thou not better never bring theſe Scriptures, that are ſo plainly againſt thee, were it not a great folly, to alledge the ſecond Commandement, to prove the worſhiping of Images; &amp; is it not as great folly in thee, to alledge Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to deny Baptiſme, that is ſo plainly for it; thou muſt as the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> do, and as thou and thy fellowes, follow them, either maintain your divices by unwriten very lyes, which you call verities, and ſo make men believe as the Church believes, or the Father of yourfami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, or the more you alledge Scripture to hold up your Idol, the more it fals, and is broken apeices.</p>
            <p>Did not <hi>Paul</hi> (ſaiſt thou) foreſee, that thing to be Idolized in his dayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No <hi>Martin,</hi> that is the falſe device of thy generation, from whom thou haſt received it, witneſs <hi>James Naylors</hi> Book, tituled a Hand held forth to the help-leſs, to lead them out of darkneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where he delivers it plainly, and groſly, in the point of Baptiſme, in which he deliver a palpable lie, as thou doſt here after him: both againſt the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> for neither did the <hi>Corinthians</hi> Idolize Baptiſme, neither did <hi>Paul</hi> complain againſt them, or deny it upon any ſuch account: the Apoſtles rather complains of them, for neglect of that eſteem which they ſhould have of that Baptiſme, in relation to Chriſt,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119118:26"/>and given it to men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12, 13, 14, 15. And for further Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I ſhall give thee ſomething to Cew the Cude upon (if thou wert a Clean Beaſt in thy feeding) which is, that the Baptiſme of repentance cannot be Idolized by any, water may be Idolized, or ſomething elſe in the Inventions of men, inſtead of that Baptiſme: any ordinance of Chriſt, (whoſe ordinances are all ordinances of faith) cannot be Idoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, for where Idolizing is, there is ſomething alſo in the room of faith: but where faith is, there is no Idol or ſelf inventions, and therefore your pretended light within is an Idol, becauſe it denys (and draws men from) the faith and obedience in that Chriſt Jeſus, who dyed at <hi>Joruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and from that reverence, and eſteem which ought to be to his teaching in Scripture; to follow, and fall down to your faithleſs I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaiſt, <hi>Paul</hi> knowing Baptiſme to be a permiſſive practiſe not a precept, laid it aſide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Let thoſe who have read <hi>Paul,</hi> and read thee judge, whether thou haſt not told a manifeſt lie of <hi>Paul</hi> in this, for <hi>Paul</hi> hath not any where ſo declared his knowledge of Baptiſme, or that he laid it aſide; If Baptiſme were not a precept, the Apoſtles were tranſgreſſors to preach, and command; and practiſe in their Maſters name, that which he had not commanded, and Baptiſme being a command, thou wouldeſt report them tranſgreſſors like to thy ſelf, ſaying, they laid aſide the practiſe and teaching of their Maſters precept: what plainer precept, to thoſe who deſires to obey the Lords command can be given, then that, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>Goe teach all Nations, and Baptize them in the Name of the Father, &amp;c.</hi> And Acts. 2.38. <hi>Repent and be Baptized,</hi> and Acts. 10.48. <hi>He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to be Baptized.</hi> Surely theſe things are plain enough to all, but ſuch as bend their tongues for deceit, and to oppoſe the truth: whatſoever is manifeſted to ſuch, to be the plain Teſtimonies of truth, yet a denyal muſt be in thoſe Children of falſhood. For as theſe who are begotten by the Imortal ſeed; to a lively hope through faith, do own and ſubmit to every command of Chriſt, though never ſo ſeeming weak, and contrary to corrupt nature: So thoſe who are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by the power of darkneſs, they hate the light, and natural in them it is to oppſe it, for there is no concord betwixt light and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; in which darkneſs if thou wert not, theſe Scriptures are plain e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and ſo plain, that thou doſt not deny them, as not thinking them to be precepts. But to maintain thy darkneſs and diſobedience aggainſt them. Thou and thy generations have had ſufficient Teſtimony in the mantenance of this truth againſt your falſhood, in perverting and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119118:26"/>denying of theſe Scriptures, to which you give no anſwer, but inſtead thereof, have blown forth big and boyſterous words of ſlander, and accuſation, from the bellows of that forge, where all your falſhood is framed: and this will appear to all who have underſtanding, and did but read that which thou and others with thee have received, both concerning the former Scriptures, and that which thou followeſt with; Where <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith he was not ſent to baptize, but to preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. Paul</hi> was ſent to preach the ſame Goſpel w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> was ſent to preach, in which was concluded the Baptiſme of Repentance, or water upon Repentance and faith, as <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. and 10.47, But neither <hi>paul</hi> or <hi>Peter</hi> were ſent to Baptize, without or before preaching; for that is the work of oppoſers, not of the meſſengers of Chriſt, and therefore was it, that <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid he was ſent to preach the Goſpel, for till preaching was received, there was none to baptize.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> did neither deny to be baptized himſelf, (as thou and thy ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration doth) as appears, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.18. with 22.16, neither did he deny to baptize others after they had heard his teaching, and believing, for then he had both denyed the command of Chriſt, <hi>Mar.</hi> 28.19. and his own practice upon thoſe he baptized, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.14, 16. for to baptize in the name of Chriſt, and deny it to be a precept, or ordinance of Chriſt; doth condemn the doer: and ſo wouldeſt thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn <hi>Paul</hi> in his righteous proceeding, according to the Goſpel: but it is a condemnation of thy ſelf, and manifeſt thee to be an enemy to truth, in aledging <hi>Paul</hi> to deny his own preaching, and practice, and the reſt of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Doth not <hi>Peter</hi> (ſaiſt thou) ſpeak plain enough to the prudent, doth he account water baptiſme any better then a figure pointing out the fubſtance, the anſwer of a good conſcience,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If thou wert not of thoſe prudent ones, to whom the things of God are hid, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.21. <hi>Peters</hi> ſpeaking would be plain to thee, to be the baptiſme of repentance; not water without repentance, nor repentance denying water: though thou wouldeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide them as all Antichriſtians have done: though <hi>Peter</hi> calls baptiſme the figure, yet he calleth the figure that ſaveth, which cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the anſwer of a good conſcience, therefore thy calling it a figure or water baptiſme, without the anſwer of a good conſcience, and that ſaveth not, ſhews how thou ſtrives to violate that Scripture and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt thy ignorance of what baptiſme is.</p>
            <p>Which of you (ſaiſt thou) would you be truly honeſt to the light of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119118:27"/>God in you, durſt poſſitively affirm ontward water to be the Baptiſme of Chriſt, Is not his a baptiſme of ſuffering?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. Martin,</hi> if outward water; (as thou haſt been told before) were the baptiſme of Chriſt, then thou, and all thy generation who have had outward water, by the order of the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized; but wanting faith according to the order of the Goſpel, you have not the baptiſme of Chriſt, they (whom thou calleſt the poor hearts) are ſo honeſt to the light of Gods truth revealed to them by the Goſpels preaching, that they, do affirm water, adminiſtred upon repentance, and faith, is the baptiſme of Chriſt, that is a cording to <hi>Peters</hi> teaching in the Scripture afore all edged. That outward water is not the figure that ſaveth but baptiſme is; and alſo they further affirm, that thy diviſion of water from repentance in baptiſme, that thou may deny the Goſpel Baptiſme, doſt manifeſt thee a child of thoſe Antichriſtain predl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors from whom thou receiveſt thy outward water. doth not thy fingling out the Baptiſme of ſuffering only, to deny the baptiſme of repentance, by reach alſo, to the denyal of the bap iſme of Chriſt: but talk not thou of the baptiſme of ſufferings, till thou ſuffer Chriſts baptiſme of repentance, to talk place in thee, none ever ſuffered for Chriſts name ſake; who denyed him in his ordinance? thou bids the poor hearts not be afraid to take up the daly Croſs, but like vallent Souldiers enter the field <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The entering into Chriſt by the Baptiſme of repentance, Is the taking up of his Croſs, and deny ill of that Baptiſme in all Ages ſince Chriſt, hath been to avoid and deny the Croſs of Chriſt, and therefore whatever croſs thou or thy fellows meets withall, Is not the Croſs of Chriſt, or worthy, of thename of ſuffering for Chriſt, or Goſpel Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; for you deny both Goſpel and Chriſt, and all your Humiliation, and pretended valiantneſs in ſuffering is from ſelf deſire to maintain your own divices: and therefore as Scripture tells, you will not be known worthy of reward.</p>
            <p>The poor hearts obedience to the teaching of Chriſt in his ordinances, as in the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of repentance doth manifeſt their love, excluding fear, in taking up the Croſe of Chriſt by which they ſtand Armed with ſtrength from God, to undergo what ever they ſhall be called to in witneſs of his truth, and if they fall in that day of tryal, their ſtreng this ſmall. And then they violate &amp; make void (as to themſelves) he Baptiſme of rapentance, they ſo much plead for, denyal of which Baptiſme (as hath been ſaid) is device to keep men from the Croſs of Chriſt, for that baptiſme brings a man to the loweſt eſtare of ſelf denyal and Humility, and to be raiſed up in the acknowledging their State of life, to be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the love and power of God, in which warrfare the Saints have alwayes got the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſo ſhall thoſe whom thou calleſt the poor hearts continuing faithful in the Lords truth, an promiſe, not giving ear to thoſe pretended lights of mens conſciences, that deny the commandments of God, and obedience to the Law of faith: And though ſuch come forth like Giants with big and furious words, railing againſt the hoſt of living God, yet the Lord will ſubdue them with Sling ſtones, and cut them off with their own Weapons <hi>Zeek</hi> 9 15. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.49, 50, 51. For what is not of God ſhall fall, and none can ſtay the conſumation determined to be powered upon the deſolate, <hi>Dan</hi> 9.27.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ionathan Ionſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:119118:27"/>
            <head>MARTINS MEDITATIONS.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ARTIN</hi> one day, ſat muſing in his mind,</l>
               <l>Of things which are, and things which after follow,</l>
               <l>And ſtudied ſore, to ſee if he could find</l>
               <l>Who Truth enjoys, and who in falſhood wallow:</l>
               <l>And as he thus ſat muſing all alone,</l>
               <l>Attendance ſtrait came to him many a one.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There firſt came in a meſſenger of light,</l>
               <l>And told him all things lodged in his heart</l>
               <l>And of the Truth gave him a glorious ſight</l>
               <l>And from falſe fained things wil'd him depart.</l>
               <l>He let him ſee the ill of their eſtate,</l>
               <l>Who make Religion nothing but a prate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They in obedience to the royall Law</l>
               <l>No Faith produce, but ſelf-inventions frame</l>
               <l>From love of heavenly truth mens mindes to draw,</l>
               <l>And keep them from the ever ſaving Name.</l>
               <l>And what they practice hath no Goſpel warrant,</l>
               <l>And thus this Meſſenger began his Errant.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And further told him if he would be ſure</l>
               <l>To walk aright, and work the work of God,</l>
               <l>And for himſelf Salvation would procure.</l>
               <l>Then muſt he follow in the holy trod</l>
               <l>Which the Apoſtles of our Lord did walk in,</l>
               <l>And not believe the vainneſſe of mens talking.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:119118:28"/>
            <lg>
               <l>He muſt the Scriptures hear in what they teach him,</l>
               <l>And yeeld himſelf unto the gracious will,</l>
               <l>Which thoſe Apoſtles of our Maſter preach him</l>
               <l>And they will ſurely teach him Chriſtian skill,</l>
               <l>And bring him to a right regenerate frame,</l>
               <l>To know the Lord and call upon his Name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Repent and be baptized ſaith this Meſſage</l>
               <l>And God will ſeal his Covenant in thy heart</l>
               <l>Deny not <hi>Martin</hi> to receive th'Embaſſage,</l>
               <l>Which God by his, doth to thee thus impart</l>
               <l>And it will bring aſſurance to thy ſoul</l>
               <l>Of heavenly favour and of ſins controul</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But if thou wilt not hear this voice of life</l>
               <l>And ſhew thy ſelf obedient to this call,</l>
               <l>Then ſeverall cries 'mongſt which there is ſuch ſtrife</l>
               <l>Will thee aſſail and round about thee fall.</l>
               <l>And with their evil Charmes and ſtrong deluſions</l>
               <l>Inthral thy mind in ſeverall ſad confuſions.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That thou mayſt hear and do thou knowſt not what,</l>
               <l>And follow men, and leave the Lord thy Saviour,</l>
               <l>Therefore ſaith he, in time be ware of that,</l>
               <l>If thou wilt gain an everlaſting favour,</l>
               <l>So ſhall thy ſoul continually be at reſt,</l>
               <l>and not with fear and vain device oppreſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Martin</hi> at this being troubled in his mind</l>
               <l>This ſacred counſel to deny, or do,</l>
               <l>A love to what was told him could not find,</l>
               <l>But from this admonition ſoon did go:</l>
               <l>For this good ſeed was ſtoln by thoſe that flie</l>
               <l>About the world betwixt the earth and skie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now a many quickly enter in,</l>
               <l>Some on this manner ſaying, ſome on that,</l>
               <l>At laſt a whited black one did begin</l>
               <l>To talk and to delude him by his chat.</l>
               <l>Humble he ſeem'd with coat and viſage trim</l>
               <l>To hide his foul deformity moſt grim.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:119118:28"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Believe not thou (quoth he) that voice that ſpake</l>
               <l>And told thee Stories of the Scriptures preaching,</l>
               <l>Hear me, who am ſent hit her for thy ſake,</l>
               <l>To let thee know, the Conſcience ſecret teaching's</l>
               <l>The Light within, to which thou muſt take heed,</l>
               <l>Not that which thou doſt in the Scripture read.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Scripture's a dead Letter, void of Life,</l>
               <l>That Chriſt, no Saviour, who at <hi>'Salem</hi> died,</l>
               <l>Thy Saviour is within thee: form and ſtrife</l>
               <l>'s amongſt men who in Scripture rules abide.</l>
               <l>Let Scripture rules alone, what light's within thee,</l>
               <l>Let that ſure light in all thy works begin thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What's Baptiſme with water but a toy,</l>
               <l>What's Bread and wine receiv'd with faith in Jeſus?</l>
               <l>A fruitleſſe form, the hid light will deſtroy</l>
               <l>Theſe outward things, which too too much diſpleaſe us,</l>
               <l>Who do deny the precepts of that Preacher</l>
               <l>Whom men call Jeſus Chriſt the Goſpel Teacher.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That outward Chriſt, who at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> died,</l>
               <l>And all thoſe outward things from him profeſ't,</l>
               <l>Are of no worth, but to be laid aſide,</l>
               <l>The Inward light will make thee theſe deteſt;</l>
               <l>And though men think through Faith to have Salvation</l>
               <l>In <hi>Mary's</hi> Son, it's a vain Imagination.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>None are redeemed, or are ſaved by him,</l>
               <l>Redemption's not by any thing without,</l>
               <l>The light within, the womans ſeed, eſpy him,</l>
               <l>That's thy Redeemer, of which have no doubt.</l>
               <l>Mind that within thee, and obey its teaching,</l>
               <l>Beleeve not Chriſt, or Scriptures preaching.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It is a Doctrine damnable and vild,</l>
               <l>To ſay the Spirit is received by preaching</l>
               <l>Of the Apoſtles faith in <hi>Mary's</hi> child,</l>
               <l>And hearing and obeying to their teaching.</l>
               <l>They'r filthy creatures, ſerpents, dogs, and ſwine,</l>
               <l>That ſo to Scriptures teachings do incline.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:119118:29"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Without the Apoſtles preaching in the Letter</l>
               <l>The Spirit is received, and Chriſt within,</l>
               <l>Look but within thee, there thoul't find him better</l>
               <l>Then by th' Apoſtles, tis the man of ſin.</l>
               <l>That bids thee hear the Apoſtles for ſalvation,</l>
               <l>All that lock there for Chriſt find deſolation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus have I told thee where thou Chriſt ſhalt find,</l>
               <l>Even in thy ſelf, thy teacher there doth dwell,</l>
               <l>Thoſe who ſeck Chriſt within the Scripture's blind,</l>
               <l>With ſuch falſe teachers ſee thou do not me'll.</l>
               <l>Obey the light within, ſo ſhalt thou be</l>
               <l>A perfect man, and from deceivers free.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This voice ſo well did <hi>Martins</hi> pallet pleaſe,</l>
               <l>That he himſelf, himſelf might onely teach,</l>
               <l>That he could be a Chriſtian now with eaſe</l>
               <l>And ne'r ſubmit to what the Scriptures Preach.</l>
               <l>The Doctrines of regeneration taught,</l>
               <l>Are now by him eſteemd a thing of naught.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He'd always Chriſt within, be ne'r was loſt</l>
               <l>So Chriſt, the Saviour, needs not come to ſave him,</l>
               <l>His Chriſt within ſaves him without that coſt,</l>
               <l>But that falſe Chriſt will even of life bereave him.</l>
               <l>This light that thus in <hi>Martin</hi> doth ariſe,</l>
               <l>Is even the light of the old Phariſees.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They would have life denying <hi>Marys</hi> Son,</l>
               <l>And of the Heavenly kingdom would be free,</l>
               <l>Without Chriſt Jeſus, and would headlong run,</l>
               <l>In ſelf-iſh lights againſt Chriſts verity.</l>
               <l>Hating the Doctrine, taught them by the Saviour,</l>
               <l>'thout whom there is no everlaſting favour.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So <hi>Martin</hi> by his meritorious works,</l>
               <l>'thout faith in Jeſus, thinks to gain Salvation,</l>
               <l>But that's the enemy which in him lurks,</l>
               <l>And fills him with a vain Imagination.</l>
               <l>To look for life where life he cannot find,</l>
               <l>Thus ſtrang Deluſions make deceivers blind.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. J.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
